<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Marcus Minucius Felix his Octavius, or, A vindication of Christianity against paganism translated by P. Lorrain.</title>
            <title>Octavius. English. 1682</title>
            <author>Minucius Felix, Marcus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50972</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2201</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24390</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08163933</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08163933</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40984</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50972)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40984)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1235:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Marcus Minucius Felix his Octavius, or, A vindication of Christianity against paganism translated by P. Lorrain.</title>
                  <title>Octavius. English. 1682</title>
                  <author>Minucius Felix, Marcus.</author>
                  <author>Lorrain, P. (Paul), d. 1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[13], 126, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for R. Royston,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Epistle dedicatory" signed: Paul Lorrain.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apologetics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Apologetics --  History --  Early church, ca. 30-600.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40984:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40984:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Marcus Minucius Felix</hi> HIS <hi>OCTAVI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S;</hi> OR, A Vindication OF CHRISTIANITY AGAINST <hi>Paganiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated by <hi>P. LORRAIN</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>R Royſton,</hi> Bookſeller to His moſt Sacred Majeſty, 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40984:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40984:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE REVEREND</hi> JOHN TILLOTSON <hi>D.D. DEAN</hi> of <hi>CANTERBURY,</hi> and <hi>Chaplain</hi> in <hi>Ordinary</hi> to <hi>His MAJESTY.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>REVEREND SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHEREAS o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> are grounded merely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Reſpect</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> or upon the proſpect of ſome <hi>Advantage</hi> to the <hi>Book,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:40984:3"/>or <hi>Author; this</hi> is more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately an Effect of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice:</hi> ſince it is by Your Encouragement that this <hi>Tranſlation</hi> appears in Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, You having been pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to peruſe and approve it. Yet this, SIR, is not all I have to alledge for this <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication:</hi> For whether I conſider <hi>You</hi> as a Zealous <hi>Defender</hi> of our <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> againſt <hi>Atheiſm;</hi> or of our <hi>Reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> againſt the <hi>Romiſh Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtion,</hi> which is the old <hi>Paganiſm</hi> reviv'd and var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd
<pb facs="tcp:40984:3"/>over; I cannot make a fitter Choice of a <hi>Patron,</hi> either for MIN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S FELIX, or myſelf, who am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>REVEREND SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt oblig'd, and Moſt devoted Servant,</hi>PAUL LORRAIN.</signed>
               <dateline>London, <date>July <hi>10. 1682.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:40984:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40984:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THOUGH a <hi>Preface</hi> to ſo ſmall a <hi>Treatiſe</hi> as this is, may by ſome be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed needleſs and ſuperfluous, yet having reaſon to believe, that the READER will not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to underſtand ſomething concerning the <hi>Book</hi> it ſelf, its <hi>Author,</hi> and the <hi>End</hi> of publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, as briefly as may be, to give <hi>him</hi> all the ſatisfaction I can.</p>
            <p>AS for the <hi>Treatiſe</hi> it ſelf (which contains a <hi>Conference</hi> or <hi>Diſpute</hi> between a <hi>Heathen</hi> and a
<pb facs="tcp:40984:5"/>
               <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> in defence of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective <hi>Religions</hi>) it has been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways accounted one of the moſt Eloquent and Curious <hi>Pieces,</hi> that <hi>Antiquity</hi> has tranſmitted to us; and in which ſo many Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſhine forth, as it is hard to determine whether it be more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent or pithy; more florid or ſound and convincing. The <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations</hi> are ſuccinct and clear; the <hi>Arguments</hi> ſtrong and perſwaſive; the <hi>Allegations</hi> pertinent and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful, and the <hi>Whole</hi> deck'd with ſo comely a grace, and ſuch lively figures of <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> as makes it truly admirable. The <hi>Heathen</hi> enters the Liſts firſt, and alledges all that can be thought of, in favour of <hi>Pagan Idolatry,</hi> and all that the <hi>Hell-born</hi> Malice of
<pb facs="tcp:40984:5"/>thoſe times, had invented againſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> preſſing it home with all the advantages that <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Learning</hi> can afford. The <hi>Chriſtian</hi> on the other ſide, with a great deal of ſoundneſs and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, overthrows all his <hi>Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> in defence of <hi>Heathen Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition;</hi> beats him with his own Weapon; demonſtrates to the eye the palpable falſeneſs of thoſe <hi>Scandals</hi> rais'd againſt the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and aſſerts their <hi>Religion</hi> with ſo much vigor and truth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents it ſo lively (as it was all beautiful in its primitive <hi>Purity</hi> and <hi>Simplicity</hi>) that it can't but greatly affect and delight the Devout READER, who muſt needs rejoyce to ſee the Natural amiableneſs and Charms of that
<pb facs="tcp:40984:6"/>
               <hi>Religion,</hi> which (alas!) the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious inventions and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitable lives of its <hi>Profeſſors</hi> have ſo miſerably diſguis'd. Beſides all this, the <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> contains ſuch an immenſe variety of <hi>Inſtances</hi> and <hi>Hiſtories</hi> of great Antiquity, ſuited to the <hi>Diſpute</hi> in hand, as makes the reading of it very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and agreeable; inſomuch, that I dare ſay, that never more <hi>Matter</hi> was crouded into ſo ſmall a <hi>Volume.</hi> But I ſhould be too tedious, ſhould I endeavour but to touch the Heads of thoſe pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar <hi>Excellencies</hi> it is adorned with; wherefore I ſhall break off here, and add a few words concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Author MINUCIUS FELIX,</hi> whom we find to have been a <hi>Roman Knight,</hi> and by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb facs="tcp:40984:6"/>a <hi>Lawyer</hi> or <hi>Advocate,</hi> who were commonly call'd <hi>Orators:</hi> And as to the Reputation he was in, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>JEROME</hi>'s Teſtimony may ſuffice for all, who calls <hi>him</hi> a <hi>Great Roman Orator.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he who peruſes the <hi>Book</hi> in <hi>Latin,</hi> ſhall find that he was no leſs. As touching the <hi>Parties</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduc'd to maintain the <hi>Diſpute,</hi> we have no further account to give of them, what they were, beſides what's here expreſs'd; though ſome ſuppoſe, that the <hi>CAECILIUS</hi> here mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, was that Great <hi>CAECILI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>US,</hi> who was afterwards ſo Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous amongſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and in remembrance of whom S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>CYPRIAN</hi> took the Name of <hi>CAECILIANUS.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:40984:7"/>
            <p>THE <hi>End</hi> of my <hi>Tranſlating</hi> this <hi>Great Orator,</hi> was chiefly that this rare and uſeful <hi>Piece</hi> might no longer walk up and down as a Stranger amongſt us, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of our familiar acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, by appearing in an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Garb; though I can't but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that the hopes I conceiv'd that my Name might exempt it ſelf from common Oblivion, by being ſeen in the <hi>Title-Page</hi> with the Famous <hi>MINUCIUS FE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIX,</hi> was no ſmall inducement to me, to undertake this Labour. But beſides all this, I thought this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> would be of ſpecial uſe in this <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> and <hi>Apoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing</hi> Age, to repreſent to our unthinking <hi>Godleſs</hi> Crew, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonableneſs of what they
<pb facs="tcp:40984:7"/>would ſo fain make themſelves and others believe, <hi>viz.</hi> That this <hi>Univerſe</hi> is an Effect of <hi>Chance,</hi> and not of <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> and that the Glorious <hi>Fabrick</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> had no <hi>Architect,</hi> but was at all adventures jumbled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into this Excellent <hi>Order,</hi> by a fortuitous Concourſe of <hi>Atoms:</hi> An <hi>Opinion</hi> ſo groſly contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to <hi>Senſe</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that it cannot be admitted by any, but thoſe who have ſhaken hands with their own Nature, and by their Vices and Debaucheries have degraded themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the Beaſts that periſh; for they know and acknowledge their <hi>Maſters</hi> and <hi>Benefactors:</hi> But theſe more Brutiſh than the <hi>Beaſts,</hi> know neither their own,
<pb facs="tcp:40984:8"/>nor the World's Great <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maker.</hi> Neither will it (as I hope) prove leſs ſeaſonable in this dark night of <hi>Apoſtaſie,</hi> to hold forth to our <hi>nominal Chriſtians,</hi> but <hi>practical Heathens,</hi> the genuine Luſtre and Brightneſs of that <hi>Holy Profeſſion,</hi> which once ſhone ſo gloriouſly in the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances</hi> and <hi>Lives</hi> of its <hi>Primitive Embracers,</hi> that it made all the World to be in love with, or to admire it; if by this means they might be brought to bethink themſelves, and at length to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into the Way of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Holineſs,</hi> from whence they are gone aſtray.</p>
            <p>AS to this <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> the READER may be pleas'd to take notice, that I have all along made
<pb facs="tcp:40984:8"/>great uſe of the <hi>French</hi> of <hi>Monſieur D' ABLANCOURT,</hi> ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily eſteem'd by Ingenious Men; yet not without having an eye to, and continual comparing of it with the <hi>Original Latin;</hi> though I never thought it fitting to tye my ſelf too ſuperſtitiouſly to the Authors <hi>Words,</hi> but deem'd it ſufficient to expreſs his <hi>Senſe;</hi> which I have been very careful not to vary from in the leaſt. For I conceiv'd it my duty where I could not attain his <hi>Graces</hi> and <hi>Ornaments,</hi> at leaſt to ſpeak his <hi>Mind;</hi> and to give the <hi>Substance</hi> of his Arguments, where my poor ability could not reach to clothe them in ſo rich a <hi>Dreſs.</hi> For all which I challenge nothing but the READER's Acceptance,
<pb facs="tcp:40984:9"/>and where it needs, his Pardon; which might perhaps be an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to me, to attempt ſomething further in the like kind hereafter.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>FAREWEL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40984:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Marcus Minucius Felix</hi> HIS <hi>OCTAVI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S;</hi> OR, A Vindication of CHRISTIANITY againſt PAGANISM.</head>
            <p>WHEN I think of my dear <hi>Octavius,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on thoſe delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful minutes we have ſpent together, I feel ſuch a pleaſure, as if I were ſtill enjoying thoſe happy days; ſo deep an impreſſion has his <hi>Idea</hi> left in my Mind, ſince my Eyes have loſt the ſight of him. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed 'tis not without cauſe, that I am ſo ſenſibly affected with the loſs of ſo Excellent and Holy a Perſon, as he was;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40984:10"/>ſeeing he always expreſs'd ſo great a love for me, that in our paſtimes, as well as moſt weighty Affairs, we ever will'd and diſlik'd the ſame things, as if one heart had been divided between us. And as he had formerly been the intimate Friend of my youthful Loves, and Companion with me in my Errors, ſo when thoſe clouds were diſpell'd, and I came out of the darkneſs of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance into the light of Truth, he did not diſdain to accept of my company, though indeed (which was the more glorious for him) he far outwent me. I ſay, as I was lately reflecting on all theſe things, I fixed my thoughts on that ſerious and important Diſcourſe which he entertain'd, in my preſence, with <hi>Caecilius,</hi> whom by means there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he brought from his vain Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the knowledge of the true Religion of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>OCTAVI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> was come to <hi>Rome,</hi> partly upon account of buſineſs, chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, perhaps, to ſee me, for whoſe ſake he made no difficulty of leaving his Family and Children in that tender
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40984:10"/>age when they are the moſt lovely; I mean, by reaſon of their Innocence; when they begin to ſpeak half words, and when their broken and faltring ſpeech makes whatever they ſay ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely delightful. It is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd with what a joy I was tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported at this unexpected felicity, of meeting ſo good a Friend, whom of a long time I had not ſeen.</p>
            <p>WHEN the firſt motions of this joyful ſurpriſal were a little over, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our being ſome days together, and telling one another our adventures, we determin'd to go to <hi>Oſtia;</hi> the Baths there, near the Sea, being very good for me, to dry up my humors, and the Vacation of the Vintage affording me leiſure for that retirement. It was at the time when the greateſt heats of the Summer begin to abate, and the ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Fruits give notice that the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt is at hand. Being arriv'd in this fair City, we went early in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to take a walk upon the Sea-ſhore, to enjoy the freſh air, which quickens the ſpirits, and imparts livelineſs to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40984:11"/>the whole body, and where the Sands, in which the footſteps make ſo ſlight an impreſſion, do not tire the Walker, but ſuffer him without wearineſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the benefit of a pleaſant and healthful Recreation. As we were thus walking on, <hi>Caecilius</hi> who was in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with us, ſeeing an Image of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rapis,</hi> as we paſs'd by, did according to the Superſtition of the Vulgar, kiſs his hand to it, in token of worſhip and reverence. Whereupon <hi>Octavius</hi> turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to me, ſaid; Brother <hi>Marcus,</hi> you do not like a good man to ſuffer one, whom you daily converſe with, to remain in ſuch groſs blindneſs, as to ſtumble at ſtones in broad day-light, which though they be ſhap'd into ſome figure, and are perfum'd and crown'd, yet ſtill are nothing but ſtones. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it concerns you, as well as him, not to let him go on in this Error.</p>
            <p>WITH this kind of diſcourſe we paſs'd through the middle of the City, and drew towards the Sea-ſide, near a wide and open place, where we ſaw the waves gently beating the ſhore,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40984:11"/>and ſmoothly ſpreading the ſand, as if they had been fitting it on purpoſe for a walk. And as the Sea is never quite calm, even when the winds are ſtill, ſo though the waves were neither high nor foaming, yet in great curles they came rowling towards the ſhore. Thus we delightfully wander'd by the Sea-ſide, and beheld the waves coming and breaking themſelves at our feet, and then returning to be ſwallow'd up again in that vaſt Element, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing along the edge of the gently bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhore, with pleaſant ſtories we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the tediouſneſs of our journey: For <hi>Octavius</hi> entertained us with a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Navigation, in ſo pleaſant a manner, that we could not grow wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry either of walking, or hearing him. And that we might not go too far, we return'd back the ſame way we came; and being arriv'd at a place where Veſſels are dry-dock'd, we ſaw ſome little Boys vying with one another at an exerciſe of making ſhells to graze, as it were, upon the water. The Sport is this: They gather ſmall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40984:12"/>ſhells on the ſhore, picking up ſuch as are the moſt ſmooth and round; then ſtooping to the ground, with all their ſtrength deliver them, ſo as they may but juſt raze the ſurface of the water; and he that makes them glide furtheſt, and gives the moſt bounds, does win the Game. Whilſt <hi>Octavius</hi> and my ſelf were looking on theſe Children, <hi>Caecili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> taking no diverſion in their ſport, nor any notice of the activity of theſe Youths, kept aloof thoughtful and melancholick, ſhewing by his clouded countenance that he had ſomething in his mind that troubled him, inſomuch that it prompted me to accoſt him with this diſcourſe. How now? What is become of that gay and charming tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which you are wont to have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven amidſt your moſt ſerious Affairs? Whereupon he reply'd, I will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal from you, that <hi>Octavius</hi> has affron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and vex'd me to the heart; for it ſeems that he does blame you, only to offend me, and accuſe you of negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, only to expoſe me as an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and blockiſh Fellow. I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40984:12"/>to ſeek my amends for this inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and to have this matter diſcuſs'd between us in good earneſt. It's like he'l ſee then, that it is a more eaſy thing to talk of theſe matters with thoſe of his own Party, than fairly and orderly to debate them with Learned Men. Let us go and ſit down upon yonder ſtones that jet out into the Sea, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Baths from the raging waves, where we may reſt our ſelves, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue the Caſe more at leiſure. We went therefore and ſate down, they placing me between them both, not out of complement or reſpect to my Quality, (for Friendſhip either finds or makes all equal) but as a Judge and Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of their diſpute, that I might the better hear the reaſons of both Parties; and keep the two Diſputants aſunder. Then <hi>Caecilius</hi> began thus: Brother <hi>Marcus,</hi> though you be already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved about the Things which are now controverted between us, ſince upon careful examination and tryal of both, you have left the <hi>Service</hi> of our <hi>Gods,</hi> and embraced <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> yet
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40984:13"/>at preſent your mind ſhould be ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that you may hold the ſcales e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, like an equal Judge inclining to neither Party; that ſo your Sentence may rather appear to be the effect of the force of our Arguments, than of your own preconceiv'd Opinion. Therefore if you'l ſit down as a Stranger, who has no acquaintance or intereſt on either ſide, it will be no hard task to demonſtrate to you, that all the things of this World are uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and doubtful, and that the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge we have of 'em, is rather Opinion than Certainty; ſo that I cannot but wonder when I ſee ſome Men ſo lazy, as rather inconſiderately to yield to the firſt Opinion that preſents it ſelf, than to be at the pains to ſearch things to the bottom. It is indeed a thing to be lamented (and which puts one into a paſſion to think on't) to ſee ſome ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant men, who have no manner of Learning, and do ſcarce throughly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand any of the ordinary Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick Arts, boldly to decide the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt important Matters in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40984:13"/>World, which have exercis'd the Wits of the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> of all Ages, and who after all, have never been able to come to a final determination of them. For Man's underſtanding is ſo little ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſuch tranſcendent knowledge, that we cannot apprehend even things that lye at our feet. And it ſeems to me a kind of impiety, to be ſo curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as to ſound the ſecrets of <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> and in our inquiries to reach af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the heights of Heaven above, or to rifle the bowels of the Earth beneath. Happy therefore, and wiſe enough ſhould we be, if according to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Oracle of Wiſdom, we could but know our ſelves, and keep our mind from this vexatious and unprofitable labour, and confine it within the bounds of Reaſon and its own medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ocrity. And if notwithſtanding our creeping on the ground, as we do, we cannot hinder our ſelves from attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to mount up to the Heavens, and to ſoar above the Stars; let us not at leaſt add this ſecond Error to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and fill the World with vain Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40984:14"/>and Fancies, on purpoſe to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright men. For whether the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Things be certain Seeds, which by a Natural propenſity have joyn'd and united themſelves together; or that the Members of all this ſpacious Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, have meerly by Chance been fram'd and ſettled in the orderly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in which they now are; What rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is there why men ſhould fancy a <hi>God</hi> Creator of the World? What, if we ſuppoſe the Fire to have kindled the Stars; and the matter whereof the Heavens are made, to have ſpread and ſuſtain'd it ſelf; that the Earth was poiſed by its own weight, and the Sea made out of the moiſture which was drain'd from that heavy lump; What ground is there in all this for this Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? for theſe Fears? What means all this Superſtition? Pray what is Man, and all other Creatures in the World, but a mixture of Elements, which in a ſhort time diſſolve themſelves, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into their firſt Being, without the help of an overſeer, workman, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of all theſe Changes? Thus by a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40984:14"/>continual confluence of the fiery parts of matter, of which the Celeſtial Lights are made, we daily behold new Suns to ſhine: And by a like cauſe the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours and Exhalations of the Earth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce Clouds, which afterwards being condenſed, and by degrees carried up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, do at laſt diſſolve themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Rain, or elſe cauſe bluſtring Winds, ratling Hail, roaring Thunder, and dazling Lightning. Which is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon alſo why theſe Meteors do caſually and indifferently diſcharge themſelves, ſometimes on the top of a Hill, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times on a Tree, ſometimes upon Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Conſecrated places, ſometimes upon Palaces, ſometimes on ſuch as fear <hi>God,</hi> and ſometimes upon thoſe that contemn him. Shall I ſpeak of the variety and uncertainty of Storms and tempeſtuous weather, wherein it is eaſy to be obſerv'd, that without any choice or exception, all things here below are turn'd topſy-tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy? Don't we ſee both good and bad involv'd in the ſelf ſame ſhipwrack, without any diſtinction of Vice and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40984:15"/>Virtue; the guilty and innocent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd in one fire; and almoſt all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedly periſh in time of Plague, and in War the beſt many times are the firſt cut off? Nay, in time of Peace, Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs is not only upon equal terms with Virtue, but prefer'd and ador'd: So that when a man conſidereth the proſperity of the Wicked, he is at a loſs what to think of them, and does not know whether he has more reaſon to deteſt their Crimes, or deſire their happineſs. Now if the World were govern'd by a Divine <hi>Providence,</hi> and the authority of a wiſe and powerful Being, ſurely <hi>Phalaris</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the <hi>Tyrant</hi> had never mounted a Throne; nor <hi>Rutilius</hi> and <hi>Camillus</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been baniſh'd, nor <hi>Socrates</hi> forc'd to take down the deadly draught. We ſee here Trees loaden with Fruits, Fields well ſtor'd with Corn, and Hills with Grapes, ready for Vintage, which promiſe a plentiful Harveſt; and all on a ſuddain, this may be utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoil'd with rain, or deſtroy'd by a tempeſt. Surely it muſt be own'd, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40984:15"/>either Truth lyes deep buried, and the ſecret ſprings and wheels of <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> are altogether unknown, or (which is the moſt probable) that <hi>Chance</hi> only governs the World with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Law or Order. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſince either the viciſſitudes and motions of <hi>Nature</hi> are uncertain, or we our ſelves certainly under the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of <hi>Fortune,</hi> how much more reaſonable and juſt is it to retain the Doctrine of our Anceſtors, and adore the <hi>Gods</hi> which our Fathers have wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp'd, and in whoſe Service we have been brought up from our infancy, than to go about to judge of Things ſo far above our reach as the Deity is? And is it not better and ſafer to believe our firſt Fore-fathers. who living in an Age of great ſimplicity, and in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry infancy of the World, deſerv'd to have their Gods either eaſie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious, or exerciſing a gentle govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment like that of Kings? For indeed we ſee all the Towns, Provinces and Kingdoms of the World have ſome Religion or other, and peculiar Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40984:16"/>each worſhipping their own <hi>Country-Gods;</hi> as the <hi>Eleuſinians</hi> do <hi>Ceres;</hi> the <hi>Phrygians, Cybele;</hi> the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daurians, Aeſculapius;</hi> the <hi>Chaldeans, Bell;</hi> the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> and <hi>Sydonians, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarte;</hi> the <hi>Scythians, Diana;</hi> the <hi>Gauls, Mercurius;</hi> and the <hi>Romans, all</hi> of <hi>them</hi> together; which is the reaſon why their Power is ſo greatly encreas'd, and themſelves become Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the whole World, having car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried their Dominion almoſt beyond the courſe of the <hi>Sun,</hi> and the bounds of the <hi>Ocean:</hi> For by the Religion and Valour of their Arms; by guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their City with the Service of the <hi>Gods,</hi> Nunneries of <hi>Veſtals,</hi> and other Chaſt <hi>Votaries,</hi> with a vaſt number of <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies;</hi> by appeaſing their angry <hi>Gods,</hi> when other Nations would have Blaſphemed them, and even at that time when <hi>Rome</hi> was ſackt, and had nothing left her but the <hi>Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tol;</hi> by adventuring (in celebrating their <hi>Myſteries</hi>) to paſs unarm'd through the Camp of their Enemies, whom they aſtoniſhed and daunted with the bold
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40984:16"/>daringneſs of their Zeal; by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill to worſhip their vanquiſhed <hi>Gods,</hi> even at the very inſtant when their Enemies having taken their City, made 'em feel the inſolence which their Victory prompted them to; by ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>Deities</hi> throughout the World, to adore them and give them Temples at <hi>Rome;</hi> nay, beſides all this, by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting Altars to unknown <hi>Deities,</hi> and the Souls of departed <hi>Heroes;</hi> And in a word, by worſhipping the <hi>Gods</hi> of all Nations, they are deſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly become the Maſters of, and have given Laws to all Nations. Which De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion of theirs hath ever been kept up amongſt 'em, and encreaſed more and more in proceſs of time: For age con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers I don't know what of Sacredneſs upon Temples and Holy Things; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the more ancient and unknown their Original is, the more are they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced. It is not therefore without reaſon, I confeſs (though I may be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken) that our Fore-fathers did ſo much betake themſelves to <hi>Divination,</hi> by obſerving the flying and chattering
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:40984:17"/>of Birds, and by conſulting the entrails of Beaſts; and did inſtitute the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of their <hi>Gods,</hi> and dedicate Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples to them. Do but look into the Hiſtories and Records of paſt times, and you will find that all theſe Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Ceremonies were ordain'd either to return thanks to the <hi>Divine</hi> Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or to divert the ſtroak of his Wrath, or to appeaſe the fury of it. Witneſs the <hi>Mother</hi> of the <hi>Gods,</hi> who at her coming into the City, made known the Chaſtity of a Lady, and deliver'd <hi>Rome</hi> from the fears of her Enemies. Witneſs the Statues of thoſe two Brothers on Horſe-back, which were erected in the ſame place where they ſhew'd themſelves, when return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the defeat of <hi>Perſes,</hi> with their Horſes out of breath and all in a foame, brought the news of the Victory, the very ſame day they had got it. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thoſe Games which were ſet up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new, upon a Dream which an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary man had, that <hi>Jupiter</hi> was offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Witneſs the <hi>Decii,</hi> who won the Battle by ſacrificing their lives for the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:40984:17"/>Service of their Country. In fine, witneſs <hi>Curtius,</hi> that noble Youth, who leapt on Horſe-back into that yawning Deep, which open'd it ſelf in the midſt of <hi>Rome;</hi> and by devoting himſelf to appeaſe the Anger of the Gods, cloſed up that dreadful Abyſs. And indeed the contempt of <hi>Divine</hi> Bodings hath occaſion'd the preſence of the <hi>Gods</hi> more often than we could have wiſh'd for; which the River <hi>Allia</hi> (that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Name) ſufficiently teacheth us, as well as the Battle of <hi>Claudius</hi> and <hi>Junius</hi> againſt the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> which was not ſo much a Fight, as a miſerable Shipwrack. The Lake <hi>Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimenus</hi> hath ſeen its waters ſtain'd and ſwoln with <hi>Roman</hi> Blood, becauſe a Conſul made light of the Verdict of the <hi>Augurs;</hi> as likewiſe at another time for ſome juſt imprecations which we ſlighted, we were made a Prey to the <hi>Parthians.</hi> But paſſing by things more remote, concerning the Birth of the <hi>Gods,</hi> and the Gifts and Preſents made to them; and omitting alſo the relations of the <hi>Poets,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:40984:18"/>that have foretold things to come, leſt <hi>Antiquity</hi> ſhould ſeem too fabulous, do but caſt your Eyes upon theſe Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, which at once are the City's Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament and Defence, and you ſhall find them more Auguſt and Glorious, by reaſon of the <hi>Divinities</hi> which inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit them, and are there ador'd, than by all the pomp of their Embelliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or riches of their Gifts and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings. From thence it is that the <hi>Priests</hi> are inſpir'd with the knowledge of future Events, and teach us how to prevent dangers to come. Here they are inſtructed to heal the ſick, to give hope to the afflicted, ſuccour to the needy, comfort to the unhappy, and eaſe to all our pains. And whilſt we are taking our reſt, we oft ſee, hear, and acknowledge thoſe very <hi>Gods,</hi> whom in the day-time we impiouſly deny, diſown and forſwear. Since therefore it is agreed by all Nations, that there are <hi>Gods,</hi> though their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Original be unknown, why ſhould we ſuffer thoſe bold and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent men, who being puffed up with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40984:18"/>I don't know what impious wiſdom, endeavour to weaken and deſtroy a belief which is no leſs uſeful and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, than it is ancient and vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable? And though <hi>Theodorus</hi> the <hi>Cyre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> or he that was before him <hi>(viz. Diagoras Melius)</hi> to whom <hi>Antiquity</hi> gave the Sirname of <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> have ſtrove to overthrow this Opinion, that they might extinguiſh all manner of Religion and Reverence of the <hi>Gods,</hi> and diſſolve the ſtrongeſt bond of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Society; yet ſhall their counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Wiſdom, never paſs for Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy in the eſteem and approbation of Wiſe and thinking Men. If the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> baniſh'd from their Country one <hi>Protagoras,</hi> becauſe he rais'd diſputes about the <hi>Gods</hi> (though he did it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a Philoſophical and inquiſitive, than profane way) and caus'd his Writings to be publickly burnt; ſhall we ſuffer men (pray give me leave in the heat of diſcourſe to ſpeak out my mind freely) I ſay, ſhall we ſuffer men of an unlawful, infamous and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Faction, without fear of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:40984:19"/>to attempt againſt the <hi>Gods;</hi> and gathering together a company of ſilly and ignorant people, eſpecially Women, who by reaſon of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and credulity of their Sex, are eaſily deceiv'd and impos'd upon; train them up to a wicked Confederacy, or rather Conſpiracy; into which they are not initiated by any holy Rites, but by impious Crimes practis'd in their Night-Conventicles, Solemn Faſts, and horrid and inhumane Feaſts? Theſe are the people that ſculk in the dark, and flee the light, who are mute in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and full of chat in their private Aſſemblies. They with horror and diſdain look upon our Temples as polluted Graves; They ſpit at our <hi>Gods,</hi> deride our Ceremonies, and pity others, whilſt themſelves are moſt of all to be pitied. They ſlight the Dignities of Prieſthood, and contemn the Sacred Purple, whilſt themſelves have ſcarce cloaths to cover their own nakedneſs; and out of a ſtrange mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and unheard-of boldneſs, they make nothing of preſent torments,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:40984:19"/>whilſt they are ſtrangely fearful of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain future miſeries; Nay, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fear of dying after Death makes them fearleſs of Death, ſo powerful an aſcendant groundleſs fears, and the falſe hopes wherewith they flatter and comfort themſelves, have got over their Spirits. And in the mean time, as Weeds ſpring faſteſt, and ill habits dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encreaſe more and more; ſo this pernicious and accurſed Sect every day waxing ſtronger and ſpreading it ſelf throughout the World, it is but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that a timely care be taken for its total extirpation and ſuppreſſion. By ſecret ſigns and tokens they know one another, and their mutual love almoſt anticipates their knowledge. They make their Luſt a part of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and ſo much doth the fooliſh and mad Superſtition of theſe People glory in their crimes, that they promiſcuouſly call one another Brothers and Siſters, and by this ſeeming holy Compellation make filthy Inceſt of that which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe were but ſimple Fornication: Which Wickedneſs of theirs is ſo much
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40984:20"/>nois'd abroad in the World, that the truth thereof cannot well be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd; no more than that other report which goes of them, <hi>viz.</hi> That by a mad Superſtition they worſhip the Head of that vile Animal [an <hi>Aſs</hi>]: Which indeed is a ſort of Worſhip ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuitable to their Lives and Manners. They are alſo ſaid to pay a great vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to the Privy parts of their <hi>Prieſts,</hi> as if they meant to adore the <hi>Genitals</hi> of their Ghoſtly Fathers. Now whether theſe Reports be true or falſe, I will not take upon me abſolutely to determine. But their Nocturnal Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies and conceal'd Devotions ſeem to be ſufficient Arguments to perſwade the truth of them; and they who tell us that they worſhip a Man who was crucified for his Villanies, and that the Wood of a Croſs conſtitutes a great part of their Devotion, do worthily attribute to them Altars ſuitable to their Crimes, by making them to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore what they deſerve. Moreover the Ceremony they obſerve upon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting any to their Religion is no leſs
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40984:20"/>horrible than notorious. A Child co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd all over with Paſte (to conceal the Murther he is deſigned for) is ſet before the new <hi>Proſelyte,</hi> who, by their command, ſtrikes his knife many times into it, until the blood run down apace from all parts, which by them is as greedily ſuckt up; and this common Crime is made the Pledge and Surety for their Silence and Secrecy. Theſe are their Sacrifices, which are worſe than all Sacriledges. As to their Feaſts, they are but too well known; concerning which our <hi>Cirthenſian</hi> Orator tells us in his Speech, that on a certain day (ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly appointed for that purpoſe) they aſſemble themſelves all together, both Men, Women, Children, Brothers, Siſters, and in a word, people of all Ages, Conditions and Sexes; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they have eaten and drunk to exceſs, and that the heat of the Wine and Meats begins to kindle their blood and provoke their luſt, they caſt a morſel to a Dog, who is ty'd to a Candleſtick, ſo far out of his reach, that in ſtriving to leap at it, he overthrows the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:40984:21"/>and puts out the Light. So that having thus rid themſelves of the only Witneſs of their infamous actions, and taking boldneſs from ſhameleſs Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they confuſedly mix themſelves together, as it happens; and therefore though it may chance ſo, that they are not all Inceſtuous in deed, yet they are all of 'em ſo in will and deſign; ſince the Sin acted by any one of them is not only conſented to, but wiſh'd by the whole Company. Several o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things of this nature there are, which I purpoſely omit, I having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready produc'd but too many inſtances of their Errors. And indeed were there nothing elſe againſt them but that of their endeavouring to conceal ſo much their Myſteries in obſcurity, it would be an evident proof of the truth of all we ſay, or at leaſt of the greateſt part thereof. For why do they ſo induſtriouſly ſtrive to hide that which they worſhip? Men are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to publiſh their honeſt actions; but ſuch as are unjuſt they ſeek to cover with ſilence and privacy. Why have
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:40984:21"/>they neither Altars nor Temples, nor any Images, at leaſt which are known? Why don't they ſpeak but in private holes and corners, whither they repair by ſtealth, if this their conceal'd Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion be not infamous and criminal? But pray, from whence, who, and where is this one only ſolitary and forſaken <hi>God</hi> of theirs, whom not one free Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, no Kingdoms do worſhip, no not the <hi>Romans</hi> themſelves who have wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp'd all the <hi>Gods</hi> of the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe? Among all the people in the World there is but that one miſerable Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who have ſerved one <hi>God</hi> alone; and yet they did it too in a publick manner, with Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Altars, Rites and Sacrifices; and notwithſtanding the power of this <hi>God</hi> is ſo inconſiderable, that both himſelf and his People are now Captives to the <hi>Romans.</hi> But what ſtrange and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful things don't they invent? They aſſert, That to this <hi>God,</hi> whom they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſee, nor can demonſtrate, men's Lives and Actions are particularly known; That he hears their words, ſearcheth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:40984:22"/>their moſt ſecret thoughts, and is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent every where; thereby making him troubleſome, reſtleſs and curious, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to impudence; for he hath a hand in, or at leaſt a knowledge of every thing; He is preſent every where, and leaves nothing unpried into. But how can this be? How can he poſſibly have an eye to every thing in particular, who has buſineſs in all places at once? Or how can he be ſufficient for all, whilſt he applies himſelf to every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular? Nor do they content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with all this; but they threaten all the World, and the Stars themſelves with an univerſal Conflagration; as if any thing could alter that Eternal Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which Nature her ſelf has eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd; the Elements break their Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or the <hi>Divine</hi> Harmony of the <hi>Spheres</hi> be diſſolv'd, for to deſtroy this wonderful <hi>Fabrick,</hi> which contains and ſurrounds us. To theſe they add ſeveral other Old Wives Fables: They tell us, That after Death their aſhes and duſt ſhall riſe again; and (by I don't know what ſtrange kind of perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on)
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:40984:22"/>they ſtedfaſtly believe thoſe Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors they have invented, and fancy themſelves already riſen and born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: Which is a double madneſs and folly, to believe that the Heavens and Stars which we leave as we found them, ſhall periſh; and that Men, whom we ſee hourly dye and have an End, as they have had a Beginning, ſhall for ever abide. And as if Dead Bodies being kept from the flames, ſhould not by length and proceſs of time be turn'd into duſt and aſhes, they will not burn their Dead, and blame us becauſe we burn ours. Do you think that it matters any thing, whether they be conſum'd in the Earth or in the Sea, or devour'd by Fire or wild Beaſts? For if Dead Bodies have any ſenſe, any manner of Burial muſt needs be a torment to them; but if they have none, that way whereby they are ſooneſt conſum'd, is the beſt. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs being prepoſſeſt with this ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous opinion, they promiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (as the Godly Party) an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting happineſs after this Life; and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:40984:23"/>threaten others (as being the Rebel Rout) with torments that ſhall have no end. I have many things to ſay here, to prove them worſe than others; but I will not take pains to make it out, ſince I think it ſufficiently done already. But were it granted that they are as righteous as others, is it not as a certain truth believ'd by moſt, That <hi>Deſtiny</hi> is the cauſe both of the good and evil, that we ſee in the World? Which is your judgment al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. For as ſome impute all humane Actions to <hi>Fate</hi> and <hi>Fortune,</hi> ſo do you to <hi>God.</hi> Which is in effect to ſay, that you have not voluntarily embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced this Sect, but <hi>God</hi> has Elected you thereunto; So that thereby you make your <hi>God</hi> an unjuſt Judge, who does not puniſh the ſinful, but the unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate. Pray tell me, ſhall you riſe again without, or with a Body? and ſhall that Body be the ſame you have now, or another? If you ſay without a Body: For my part I don't believe there is either Life, Soul, or Senſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Body. And how with a Body?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:40984:23"/>It cannot be your own; for that is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready waſted. Shall it be another? Then it will be a new body, and not the old one repair'd. Beſides, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ages are paſt and gone; and yet who has ever been ſeen to riſe and come to Life again, though but for a ſmall time (as the <hi>Poets</hi> feign <hi>Proteſilaus</hi> did) that we might have ſome ground to believe this <hi>Paradox?</hi> Indeed theſe Stories are but <hi>Chimaeras</hi> of a crack'd brain, and the vain comforts which <hi>Poets</hi> have invented and pleaſantly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd for their own and others diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And theſe old Fables new vamp'd, your credulity entertains and applies them to your <hi>God.</hi> Why don't you ſuffer the experience of things preſent to teach you, at leaſt, how vain theſe your promiſes and hopes of the future are? Poor wretches! You might learn what will be your Fate after Death, by the miſeries of Life which you now endure. The moſt and the beſt of you (as you ſay your ſelves) are ready to ſtarve, being in want of all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for this mortal Life, and under
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:40984:24"/>great troubles and miſeries; which <hi>God</hi> ſuffers and takes no notice of; An evident proof, that he either will not, or can't afford you any relief; and by conſequence is either impotent or unjuſt. Thou who flattereſt thy ſelf with an immortality after this Life, art thou not ſenſible of thy condition? Canſt thou deny thy weakneſs, when thou trembleſt at dangers, when thou burneſt in a Feaver, when thou art rack'd with pain? Miſerable delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion! Not to own one's miſery, even when one feels it! But to leave theſe common Matters; behold there are executions, puniſhments and torments that await you, and croſſes, not to be ador'd by you, but endur'd; with fires and flames, which you own your ſelves afraid of, whilſt you foretel and threaten them to others. Where is that <hi>God</hi> that can raiſe the Dead, but not relieve the Living? Are not the <hi>Romans,</hi> without the aſſiſtance of your <hi>God,</hi> become the Maſters of the World, and of your ſelves too, whilſt you in the mean time refrain from lawful
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:40984:24"/>pleaſures, and entertain your ſullen hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour with troubleſome fears and anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous thoughts? You are never ſeen at any publick Spectacles and Triumphs; nor do you ever frequent our ſolemn Feaſts and Combats in honour of our <hi>Gods.</hi> You abhor the Meats which <hi>Prieſts</hi> have touch'd, and are afraid to taſte the Wine that hath been preſented on our Altars; So that it ſeems you ſtand in ſome awe of thoſe very <hi>Gods,</hi> whom you deny. You wear no Garlands on your Heads, and reſerve your Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Perfumes for the Dead; Nor do you ſo much as adorn the Graves of your deceaſed Friends with Chaplets. You look pale and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and are indeed real Objects of pity; but it muſt be of the pity of our <hi>Gods,</hi> for yours take no notice of you. Miſerable Wretches! who deprive your ſelves of the enjoyments of this Life, and deceive your ſelves in the expectation of another. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if you have any wiſdom or mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty left, give over gazing upon the Stars, and ſearching into the <hi>Deſtiny</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:40984:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:40984:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:40984:26"/>of the World; And think it enough to look to your own feet; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for ſuch rude and unlearned People as you are, who hardly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand matters of a Civil concernment, much leſs are able to diſcourſe of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi> and <hi>Heavenly</hi> things. But if you have ſuch an itch of <hi>Philoſophizing,</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Example of <hi>Socrates</hi> (you who think ſo highly of your ſelves) that was the Prince of Wiſdom: All know the anſwer he was wont to make to thoſe that ask'd him any Queſtions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Matters of <hi>DIVINITY. What's above us</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>does not concern us.</hi> For which he merited the Praiſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Wiſdom, from the mouth of the <hi>Oracle</hi> it ſelf; and he himſelf was ſenſible, that it was not for his knowing all things, that <hi>Apollo</hi> had pronounced him the Wiſeſt of all <hi>Greece;</hi> but becauſe he had learn't this one thing, <hi>That he knew nothing.</hi> This therefore is the greateſt Wiſdom of all, for a Man to confeſs his own ignorance. Upon this bottom were founded the Opinions of <hi>Arceſilas, Carneades</hi> and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40984:26"/>ſeveral other <hi>Philoſphers</hi> of the <hi>Ancient Academy,</hi> who thought it ſafeſt not to determine any thing in Matters of any difficulty. And indeed this modeſt and doubtful way of <hi>Philoſophizing</hi> is the beſt, ſeeing it is warineſs in the Ignorant, and wiſdom in the Learned. It was this, which gain'd ſo much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration and eſteem to <hi>Simonides,</hi> whoſe admirable ſlowneſs and caution deſerves to be propos'd as an Example to be imitated by all Poſterity. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ask'd of <hi>Hiero</hi> what his belief and opinion was concerning the <hi>Gods,</hi> he at firſt demanded a day to conſider of it: The next day after being queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about the ſame thing, he deſir'd two days more; the third time he crav'd as many more; and ſo from that time forth he ſtill doubled the number: At which the King ſtanding amaz'd (not being able to gueſs the reaſon of ſo many delays) and preſſing him to anſwer the Queſtion without any further put-offs; <hi>The more</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>O King, that I ſtudy and meditate of the Thing you enquir'd of me, the more
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:40984:27"/>obſcure it grows.</hi> Thus (methinks) we ought to leave ſuch things as are intri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and uncertain, undetermin'd, and not boldly give our Verdict in a Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wherein the Wiſeſt Men are at a great loſs, and uſe to ſuſpend their Judgments; nor be too forward to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve and decide Controverſies, whilſt the ableſt and moſt Learned are yet in doubtful deliberation about them; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this is the ready way either to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all manner of Religion, or to introduce the moſt fulſome Superſtition and intolerable Slavery.</p>
            <p>WHEN <hi>Caecilius</hi> had thus made an end, Well (ſaid he, with a ſmiling countenance; for the earneſtneſs of his Diſcourſe had appeas'd his Anger) what to all this ſays our <hi>Octavius</hi> of the Race <hi>Plautus</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>the chief of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, and the meaneſt of Philoſophers?</hi> Soft (ſaid I to him) you had better ſpare your braggs, and not begin your triumph till you have got the Victory; nor pleaſe your ſelf too much with the fine Speech you have made. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that Truth, and not Vain-glory,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:40984:27"/>is the Thing we contend for. And indeed it is not your Diſcourſe that gives me the greateſt trouble (though I muſt confeſs that I was extreamly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken with it, becauſe it was both very witty and graced with admirable va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety) but I am ſorry to ſee, that the probability of Things does change face, according to the abilities and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of thoſe that diſcourſe them, and that the moſt evident truth often is obſcur'd by the weakneſs of thoſe who manage it. Men are apt to be carry'd away with an Eloquent Speech, and to aſſent to every thing that is plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly ſaid, and to be diverted from the conſideration of what's treated of, without diſcerning Truth from Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, or conſidering that as a Paradox may ſometimes be true, ſo a likely thing often is falſe: And therefore the eaſier they are to believe the aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of others, the oft'ner are they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd and convinc'd by thoſe who look nearer into the Matter: So that being nettled at laſt to ſee themſelves deceiv'd at every turn, they caſt the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40984:28"/>blame of their own raſhneſs upon the doubtfulneſs and uncertainty of all things, and had rather condemn every thing and believe nothing at all, than concern themſelves in Matters that are ſo doubtful, and lyable to miſtake. 'Tis therefore our intereſt to have a care, leſt this ſhould make us have an averſion for all manner of Diſcourſe and Conferences, or (which is worſe) make us diſtaſt and hate the company of Men. For thoſe who eaſily believe any thing, finding themſelves frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deceiv'd, by perſons whom they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore eſteem'd homeſt and good Men, fall into another extreme, which is, That they ſuſpect all the World, and miſtruſt even thoſe in whom they have reaſon to repoſe the greateſt confidence. Wherefore ſince it is ſo natural for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one to employ all their might in the vindication of their own Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſince alſo in ſuch Diſputes as theſe, the one has commonly more Truth on his ſide, though obſcure and unperceiv'd, and the other more Wit and Eloquence, even ſo far as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40984:28"/>to perſwade things that are not; it is our Duty to ponder and conſider of the Whole, with all the ſtrictneſs and exactneſs imaginable, that we may pick out, approve and receive what's good in it, contenting our ſelves to commend what is wittily ſaid, without believing it.</p>
            <p>YOU tranſgreſs the bounds, and keep not the meaſures of an equal Judg (reply'd <hi>Caecilius</hi>) by interrupting our Diſpute with a Diſcourſe that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to weaken the ſtrength, and take away the credit of what I have ſaid; eſpecially ſeeing <hi>Octavius</hi> has all the Particulars of my Reaſoning whole and entire before him, and may anſwer and refute them, if he can: And for all your reflecting on my Diſcourſe, if I be not miſtaken, I have done nothing but what's for the intereſt of us both; having endeavour'd only to exhibite a <hi>Compendium</hi> of the Matters in Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between us, to the end that what I have deliver'd, might be examin'd, rather by the force and ſoundneſs of Reaſon, than by any high and pompous
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:40984:29"/>Eloquence. And we ought not any more take off our attention from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the Things themſelves (as you well obſerve) ſince our <hi>Januarius</hi> is now preparing and raiſing himſelf to take his turn, if we can but have the patience to hear him with ſilence.</p>
            <p>I SHALL ſpeak (ſaid <hi>Octavius</hi>) as much to the purpoſe as I can. But we muſt firſt endeavour to wipe off all inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, calumnies and reflections, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel thoſe clouds with the light of Truth. To begin therefore, I muſt firſt of all tell you plainly, That you have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd ſo great an uncertainty about the things you ſpoke of, that I doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed whether you fail'd in point of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Knowledge, or were blinded by Error. For ſometimes you ſaid that you believ'd there were <hi>Gods;</hi> and ſometimes again, that you did not know, what to believe of 'em; as if you had a deſign by your ambiguous Expreſſions to avoid the dint of my Anſwer. But I can't think this of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilius;</hi> Theſe crafty tricks are beneath the greatneſs of his Wit, and the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40984:29"/>of his temper. But he does like thoſe, who knowing not the way, ſtop when it divides into many, and are at a loſs which to take, becauſe they cannot believe them all right, and dare not chuſe any one: In like manner he who hath no firm judgment of Truth, is doubtful and divided in his Opinion about it, according as the reaſons on either ſide do incline and ſway him by turns. Therefore it is no wonder if <hi>Caecilius</hi> alſo be toſs'd to and fro by contrary Opinions. Which that he may no longer be, I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him of the Variety of his Errors, by repreſenting Truth to him which is but one, and ſo ſettle and eſtabliſh him for ever. And becauſe he takes it ſo heinouſly, that unlearned and poor ignorant people (as he calls us) ſhould maintain any Diſpute about <hi>Divine</hi> Matters; he muſt underſtand, that all Men are born reaſonable Creatures, without any diſtinction of Age, Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or Sex, and owe not their Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to <hi>Fortune,</hi> but to <hi>Nature.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that <hi>Philoſophers</hi> and other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:40984:30"/>Inventors of Arts and Sciences, were accounted but mean people, il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>literate and poor, till their wiſdom made them Famous; So true it is, that the Rich who idolize their Treaſures, make more account of their Gold, than of Heaven; whereas ſuch poor Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows as we, have always been the Searchers-out of Wiſdom and Teachers of it to others. Whereby we may plainly ſee, that Wit and Wealth do not always go together; neither is it ſo much the Effect of great Study and Induſtry, as an advantage of Nature. Men ought not therefore to quarrel, or be angry, when they ſee others make it their buſineſs to inquire into the truth of <hi>Divine</hi> Myſteries, and declare the underſtanding they have of them; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we ought not to regard ſo much the Authority or Quality of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puter, as the Weight and Truth of what is ſaid. The ſtrength of Reaſon appears moſt clearly, when the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is ſtript of all external Ornaments and Flouriſhes, not painted and ſet off with an artificial Grace and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:40984:30"/>but ſupported by Truth, which is the Rule of Right and Wrong. Not that I deny, for all that, what <hi>Caecilius</hi> has given himſelf ſo much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to prove, <hi>viz.</hi> That Man ought to know himſelf, what he is, from whence, and for what end; Whether he be compounded of the Elements, or made up of Atoms; or rather fram'd, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion'd, and animated by GOD himſelf. But this we cannot reſolve without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring into the nature of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, ſeeing both theſe things have ſo near a relation, and are ſo ſtraitly linked to one another, that we cannot rightly apprehend what Man is, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a diligent enquiry into the nature of the <hi>Deity;</hi> nor be able to manage the civil Affairs of this World, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being acquainted with the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of this great City of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe. And indeed it being this eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, that makes us differ from Brutes, that whereas they are continually ſtoop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downwards to the ground, look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no higher than their Food; we on the contrary, who have our Faces rais'd
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40984:31"/>upwards to behold Heaven, and are endued with the uſe of Speech and Reaſon, which teaches us to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>GOD,</hi> to perceive and imitate Him; we cannot without guilt ſhut our Eyes againſt this clear Light, which continually glares upon our Senſes; it being the higheſt kind of Sacriledge to ſeek that on Earth, which is not to be found but in Heaven. And to ſpeak the truth, one muſt be blind and ſenſeleſs, to fancy all this great and admirable Fabrick of the World, to have been form'd by a fortuitous concourſe of blind, ſenſeleſs, and unthinking Atoms, rather than by the unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Wiſdom and immenſe Power of a <hi>God.</hi> For what can be more plain, evident or conſpicuous (whether we lift up our Eyes to Heaven, or caſt them down to the Earth) than that there is an inconceivably-powerful and wiſe Spirit, which does inſpire, influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, move, cheriſh, and conduct whole Nature, and every part of it? Do but behold the Heavens; Let your thoughts out into the vaſtneſs of their
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:40984:31"/>Extenſion; conſider the ſwiftneſs of their courſe; view them by night, when they ſparkle, and are all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpangl'd with Stars; or by day, when they are all bright and reſplendent from the Sun; and you will eaſily diſcern the wonderful and <hi>Divine</hi> skill of the Supream Governour in the ordering and poizing of all theſe. Again, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how the Sun by his courſe through the Zodiack meaſures out the Year, and diſtinguiſhes its Seaſons, as the Moon does the Months by her increaſe and decreaſe. What ſhall I ſay of this continual viciſſitude of Light and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which affords us the agreeable and neceſſary enterchange of Labour and Reſt? But I muſt leave the further diſcourſe of the <hi>Stars</hi> to the <hi>Aſtrologers,</hi> whoſe proper buſineſs it is to inquire into their Virtues and influences, and who teach us, which of them rule the Winds, and inform the wary Mariner in the Art of Navigation; and which of them determine the time for Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Reaping, and are the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Almanack of the laborious Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40984:32"/>From all which it is unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably evident, that theſe Wonders could never have been created, fram'd and diſpos'd in that excellent Order, without the perfect Wiſdom of the Supream <hi>Artiſt;</hi> ſeeing we cannot ſo much as know or underſtand them, without a great ſagacity of mind and reaſon. What ſhall we ſay of that exact Diſpoſal of Time and Seaſons, wherein we do not know which we are to admire moſt, their Conſtancy or their Variety? How loudly do they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim their <hi>Divine</hi> Author, and Wiſe Director! The <hi>Spring</hi> is not more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant by its fair Days and Flowers, than the heat of <hi>Summer</hi> is uſeful and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to ripen the Fruits of the Earth; and the liberal Plenty of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn</hi> is not more joyful, than the wet and froſt of <hi>Winter</hi> is needful. Which Order might eaſily be diſturbed, if it were not diſpenſed by the ſteady Hand of <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom.</hi> Oh! the Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Providence!</hi> which has allay'd the nipping froſts of <hi>Winter,</hi> and ſcorching heats of <hi>Summer,</hi> with the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40984:32"/>intervening temperature of the <hi>Spring</hi> and <hi>Autumn;</hi> and that with ſuch exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctneſs, that the change of theſe extreams of heat and cold, is ſo far from being intolerable, that it is even eaſie and delightful, giving us the pleaſure of variety, and yet ſliding gently and inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly from one extremity to another. Caſt your eye upon the Sea, and to your amazement you ſhall ſee how the looſe Banks of Sand give a check to its proud and raging Waves. Conſider the wonderful ebbings and flowings of the <hi>Ocean;</hi> Behold the Springs whoſe waters flow continually; View the Rivers which purſue their uninterrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed courſe without ceaſing, and ever returning to that vaſt Deep, which is the Center of their Emanation: Take a proſpect of thoſe vaſt Woods and Forreſts, which deck and grace the face of the Earth; they are all fed from its bowels, and yet the Earth is never the leſs. What ſhall I ſay of that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and uſeful diſpoſal of the ſteepneſs of Mountains, the riſings of Hills, the vaſt extenſion of Plains? Or what ſhall
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:40984:33"/>I ſay of ſuch numberleſs numbers of Creatures, who are (each of them) ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally furniſh'd with their peculiar Weapons of defence; ſome are armed with horns, others fenced with teeth; ſome ſtrength'ned with hoofs, others ſharp'ned and edged with claws; ſome appointed with ſtings and ſpurs, others defended with a prickly and unacceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble skin; whilſt others again ſecure themſelves by the lightneſs of their heels, or ſwiftneſs of their wings; <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> having beſtow'd on every one of them either ſtrength or cunning for their own defence? But above all, the perfection and beauty of the Shape of <hi>Man,</hi> proclaims and owns <hi>GOD</hi> to have been the <hi>Artiſt</hi> that fram'd it. His up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Stature, his rais'd Countenance, in the upper part whereof the eyes are poſted as on a Watch-tower, and where all the other Senſes have their ſeveral Stations and Quarters allotted them, as in a Caſtle or Citadel. We ſhould never have done in going about to treat in particular of all theſe Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: There is not one part in Man,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40984:33"/>which is not ornamental and graceful, as well as neceſſary: And what is yet more admirable is, That the ſame Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure which is common to us all, is diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſified by ſuch an infinite variety of Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in each of us, that as there is a likeneſs in all, ſo there is in every one ſomething that makes him unlike to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. Beſides, how wonderful is the manner of our Birth? How ſtrong and prevalent the deſire of begetting our Like? Upon whom can you father theſe Wonders but upon <hi>GOD</hi> alone, who ſwells the breaſts with milk, againſt the time the Infant breaks his Priſon, and comes to breath the free and open Air, ſuiting their nice tenderneſs with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionate delicate nouriſhment? Nor do's this bountiful <hi>GOD</hi> content himſelf to take a general care of the Univerſe, but provides alſo for each part of it. What <hi>Great Britain</hi> wants of the heat of the Sun, is made up by the warm Vapours which ariſe from the Sea that ſurrounds it. The overflowing of the River <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> ſerves <hi>Egypt</hi> inſtead of Rain. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates</hi> makes <hi>Meſopotamia</hi> fruitful, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40984:34"/>the River <hi>Indus</hi> is ſaid both to ſow and water thoſe <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Parts. If perchance you ſhould come into a houſe, and there find all the Rooms richly furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, beautified and adorned, would you not without the leaſt heſitancy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That there is ſome Lord and Owner of it, who is far better than all this rich and glorious Furniture; ſo likewiſe in this ſtately Palace of the World, when you take a view of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, and that <hi>Providence, Order</hi> and <hi>Law,</hi> which diſpenſeth and directs all things in them, doubt, if you can, that there is a Lord and Father of this great Family, whoſe Glory far tranſcends that of the Sun, Moon and Stars, and who is more beautiful than the moſt lovely part of it. But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, ſince there is no doubt whether there be a <hi>Providence</hi> or not, you may think it a Queſtion whether there be but one or many, that have a hand in the adminiſtration of this Celeſtial Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, it will not be a hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to fix this your incertainty, if you will but attentively conſider the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40984:34"/>of the Earth, which are but ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Copies of the One Heavenly Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Empire. When did ever a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch either admit of a Partner in his Soveraignty, in full truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, or lay him aſide without blood? I omit ſpeaking of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> who refer'd the choice of their Prince to the neighing of an Horſe; and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely paſs-by that old Story of the <hi>Theban</hi> Brothers. All the World knows what diſſenſion there aroſe between two Twins, which of them ſhould be King over a Company of Shepherds, and their poor Cottages. The Wars of <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi> have ſpread themſelves over the whole World, and the Fortune of ſo vaſt an Empire was not big enough to ſatisfie theambition of two ſo nearly ally'd, as Father and Son-in-Law: You may from theſe inſtances eaſily judge of the reſt. The Bees can ſuffer no more than one King; Flocks follow one Leader, and every Herd has its own Ruler: And can you im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agine the Supreme <hi>Power</hi> of Heaven to be divided, and that the Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:40984:35"/>of that only true and <hi>Divine</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy is ſhared amongſt many? Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when you conſider, that <hi>GOD,</hi> the Father of all things, has neither Beginning nor End; and as he gives Beginning to all other things, ſo an Eternity and perpetuity of Being to himſelf. Who before this World was made, was a World to Himſelf; who by his Word commanded all things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Being, governs them by his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and perfects them by his Power. He cannot be ſeen, becauſe he is more bright and glorious than our ſight can endure to behold: Neither can He be comprehended, being greater than our minds, infinite, immenſe and only known to Himſelf; what He is indeed, our breaſts are too narrow to conceive; and we can never form a worthy noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Him, but when we own Him Ineſtimable and Incomprehenſible. May I ſpeak what I think: Whoſoever fancies he knows the Greatneſs of <hi>GOD,</hi> has already leſſen'd it; and therefore he who would not leſſen it, muſt not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to know it. Neither do thou
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:40984:35"/>enquire after his Name; His Name is <hi>GOD.</hi> 'Tis then we ſtand in need of Names, when we are to divide a multitude into particulars, by their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing Titles, and proper appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. But <hi>GOD</hi> being alone and by himſelf, the Name of <hi>GOD</hi> muſt wholly belong to Him, and to none elſe: For if I call Him Father, you'l be apt to think Him an Earthly One; if I call Him King, you'l fancy Him a Worldly Prince; if I call Him Lord, you'l apprehend Him Mortal. Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract but theſe additions of Names from our groſs imagination, and you'l ſee Him in his own Brightneſs and Glory. Beſides, in this I have the general aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all Men, concurring with me. Mind the Common-people; When they lift up their hands to Heaven, whom have they in their mouths but <hi>GOD?</hi> Their ordinary Saying is, <hi>GOD is great, GOD is true;</hi> and ever and anon <hi>[If it pleaſes GOD:]</hi> Which Words, though they contain the Confeſſion of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> yet are as well the Voice of <hi>Nature</hi> in the Common People.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40984:36"/>Yea thoſe who will have <hi>Jupiter</hi> to be the Soveraign of the Univerſe, do only miſtake in the Name; but agree with us in the Thing it ſelf, That there is but One only <hi>Power.</hi> The <hi>Poets</hi> alſo in their Verſes celebrate <hi>One Father both of the Gods and Men;</hi> and ſay, <hi>That the Minds and Thoughts of Men are ſuch as GOD every day puts into them.</hi> And what ſhall we ſay of <hi>Virgil?</hi> Does not he ſpeak yet more clearly and more near to Truth, when he ſaith, <hi>That in the beginning there was a Spirit, which inwardly cheriſhed and foſter'd both Heaven and Earth; and that all the Parts of them were actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated by a Mind infuſed throughout the Whole; and that from thence, Men and all other Creatures derive their Original?</hi> The ſame <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Poets</hi> calls in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place this Mind and Spirit <hi>GOD,</hi> as where he ſaith, that <hi>GOD is diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed throughout the vaſt Extent of the Earth and Seas, and of the high Heaven; and that from Him, Men and Beaſts, Rain and Lightning do proceed.</hi> And what do we ſay elſe, but that <hi>GOD</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:40984:36"/>is an Eternal Mind, Reaſon and Spirit? Let us take a view, if you pleaſe, of the Opinions of <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> and you will find that though they ſeem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, yet they all agree in this Matter. And omitting thoſe rude and primitive Men, who by their Sayings purchaſed the Name of <hi>Sages; Thales</hi> the <hi>Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian,</hi> who was before them all, and who firſt maintain'd any Diſpute con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Celeſtial Things, held that Water was the Original Matter of all things, and that <hi>GOD</hi> was that Mind, or Underſtanding Spirit, who fram'd them out of it: Which is certainly a more profound and ſublime Account con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Water, and its actuating Spirit, than could proceed from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of Man, without the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Divine</hi> Revelation. Thus you plainly ſee that the Opinion of the firſt of <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> does entirely concur with ours. After him <hi>Anaxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menes</hi> and <hi>Diogenes Apolloniates</hi> make God to be Air, but Immenſe and Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and in aſcribing theſe perfections to the Divinity, they alſo conſent with
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:40984:37"/>us. <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> was of opinion, that <hi>GOD</hi> was an Infinite Spirit, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining and moving all things. <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> calls Him a Mind penetrating all things and diffus'd through the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, taking care of, and giving Life to all the Creatures therein. <hi>Zeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes</hi> affirms, That <hi>GOD</hi> is an Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated Infinity, or a Spirit joyn'd with Infinite Matter. <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> declar'd, That there were ſeveral <hi>Gods,</hi> belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſeveral Countries; but that there was but <hi>One</hi> Principal and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign amongſt them all, who was <hi>GOD</hi> by Nature. <hi>Speuſippus</hi> was of opinion that <hi>GOD</hi> was nothing elſe but a Natural <hi>Power,</hi> quick'ning and governing all things. Yea, and does not <hi>Democritus</hi> himſelf (though he was the firſt Inventor of Atoms) often call <hi>Nature,</hi> which is the Former of all <hi>Ideas</hi> and Underſtanding, <hi>GOD; Strato</hi> calls Him <hi>Nature;</hi> And even <hi>Epicurus,</hi> who either believed that there were no <hi>Gods;</hi> or if there were, that they were idle, and without any concern about the things of this
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:40984:37"/>World; yet ſets <hi>Nature</hi> above them. As for <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> though he ſeem ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times divided in his thoughts, about this Matter; yet he poſitively aſſerts <hi>One</hi> Soveraign Power: For ſometimes he ſaith, That an Underſtanding Spirit is <hi>GOD;</hi> ſometimes, that the World is <hi>GOD;</hi> and then again, he will have <hi>GOD</hi> to govern the World. <hi>Heraclides</hi> of <hi>Pontus</hi> aſſerts <hi>GOD</hi> to be a <hi>Divine</hi> Spirit, but with ſome incertainty; For ſometimes he attributes the Supremacy to the <hi>Divine</hi> Spirit, and ſometimes to the World it ſelf. <hi>Theophraſtus, Zeno, Chryſippus</hi> and <hi>Cleanthes</hi> do likewiſe vary in their Opinions; Yet all of them at laſt agree in One <hi>Providence,</hi> which ſuperin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends the Whole. For <hi>Cleanthes</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times affirms <hi>GOD</hi> to be a Spirit; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that He is an Aethereal Fire; but moſt frequently calls Him, Reaſon. His Maſter <hi>Zeno</hi> holds a <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Law, and ſometimes <hi>Fire,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Reaſon,</hi> to be the firſt <hi>Cauſe</hi> of all <hi>things.</hi> He alſo evidently reproves and convinceth the common Error about the <hi>Gods,</hi> by ſhewing that <hi>Juno</hi> is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40984:38"/>but the Air, <hi>Jupiter</hi> Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>Neptune</hi> the Sea, and <hi>Vulcan</hi> the Fire; And that many of their other <hi>Gods</hi> are but the Elements dreſs'd up in other Names. <hi>Chryſippus</hi> is much of the ſame Opinion; for with him, ſometimes a <hi>Divine</hi> Power and a <hi>Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal</hi> Nature is <hi>GOD,</hi> and at other times the World, and a fatal Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and imitates <hi>Zeno</hi> in his interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Fables of the <hi>Gods,</hi> which are found in <hi>Homer, Heſiod,</hi> and <hi>Orpheus.</hi> In like manner <hi>Diogenes</hi> the <hi>Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> was us'd in his Diſcourſes to declare, That <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s Brain being with child and deliver'd of <hi>Minerva,</hi> and other like Stories, were not an account of the true Original of their <hi>Gods,</hi> but of ſome other things couch'd under thoſe Fables. <hi>Xenophon</hi> the Diſciple of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> holds, That the ſhape of the true <hi>GOD</hi> cannot be ſeen, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently is not to be ſearcht after. <hi>Ariſto</hi> of the Iſle of <hi>Chios,</hi> ſays, That he is altogether incomprehenſible: Both which <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> had doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs a right ſenſe of the <hi>Divine</hi> Majeſty,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40984:38"/>in that they deſpair'd of ever fully un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Him. As for <hi>Plato,</hi> he does more openly and clearly ſpeak of <hi>GOD,</hi> and does leſs miſtake, both as to the Name and the Thing it ſelf; and his Diſcourſes might have been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted altogether Heavenly, but that they are here and there blemiſh'd and tainted with his Politicks. In his <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maeus</hi> he calls <hi>GOD</hi> by his Own Name, and declares Him to be the Father of this Univerſe, the Creator of the Soul, and the Architect of Heaven and Earth; who by reaſon of his ſuperlative and incomprehenſible Power and Majeſty, is hard to be found, and when found, cannot poſſibly be expreſs'd and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd: Which are, in a manner, the very ſame things which we ſay; for we alſo know <hi>GOD,</hi> and own Him to be the Parent of the World; but unleſs we be demanded, we do not ſpeak publickly of Him.</p>
            <p>THUS I have rehears'd the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of almoſt all the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> whoſe glory it is, that they have all pointed at <hi>One</hi> and the ſame <hi>GOD,</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:40984:39"/>though under various Names; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it would make a Man think, either that our <hi>Chriſtians</hi> now are <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> or that the ancient <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers</hi> were <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> Now if it be granted that <hi>Providence</hi> rules the World, and is govern'd by the Will and Counſel of the <hi>One</hi> only <hi>GOD;</hi> then ought not we to ſuffer our ſelves to be impos'd upon with the ſilly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of <hi>Antiquity,</hi> which are both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to Reaſon, and condemn'd by the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> of ancient Times. Our Fathers indeed were ſo credulous, as to believe things altogether mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous and inconſiſtant, as a <hi>Scylla</hi> with ſeveral Bodies, a <hi>Chimaera</hi> with many ſhapes, an <hi>Hydra</hi> that receiv'd a new life from his happy Wounds, and <hi>Centaures,</hi> which were Horſe and Man united and growing together. In ſhort, they very readily believ'd what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever any one was pleas'd to feign or fancy; as Men's being metamorphos'd into Birds; Beaſts into Men, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain Men into Flowers and Trees; with ſo many other fabulous things,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40984:39"/>which, had they ever been, would hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſtill; but becauſe they cannot be, are hereby ſufficiently demonſtrated never to have been. Their Opinions concerning the <hi>Gods</hi> were likewiſe full of inconſiderate credulity and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant ſimplicity; for by giving Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Worſhip to their Kings, and deſiring by Pictures and Statues to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeve their memory, after their Death, they at laſt made a Religious Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of that which at firſt was only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to comfort themſelves for the loſs of them. For before the World was open'd by <hi>Commerce</hi> and <hi>Trade,</hi> and that <hi>Nations</hi> had mixt their <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> together, every one of them ador'd their firſt Founder, or Famous Leader, or ſome Queen Chaſt, and valiant above her Sex; or an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventor of ſome uſeful and neceſſary Art or Calling; as conſidering that the Memory of ſuch Renowned Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, well-deſerved to be preſerv'd by them; ſince by this means they at once gave a reward to the Virtue of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, and an example to Poſterity.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40984:40"/>Read the Writings of Wiſe-men, and particularly of the <hi>Stoicks,</hi> and you will acknowledge with me, that Men have been worſhip'd as <hi>Gods,</hi> either for their good Deeds, or their Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. <hi>Euhemerus</hi> gives us an exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Birth, Countries and Names, as alſo the ſeveral Places where they were buryed; particularly he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanceth in <hi>Jupiter</hi> call'd <hi>Dictaeus,</hi> from the Mountain <hi>Dictae</hi> in <hi>Candia,</hi> where he was nurs'd; and <hi>Apollo</hi> nam'd <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phicus,</hi> from the City <hi>Delphos</hi> in <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> a Province of <hi>Greece;</hi> and <hi>Iſis,</hi> who had the Sirname of <hi>Pharia,</hi> from the Iſland <hi>Pharos</hi> in <hi>Egypt;</hi> and <hi>Ceres,</hi> who was ſtyl'd <hi>Eleuſina,</hi> from the City <hi>Eleuſis</hi> in <hi>Achaia,</hi> where ſhe was more particularly worſhip'd. <hi>Prodicus</hi> tells us, that they were reckon'd among the <hi>Gods,</hi> who by rambling through the World, were the firſt Inventors of Huſbandry, and by this means became uſeful to Mankind. And <hi>Perſeus</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſeth much at the ſame rate; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that it was from this ground, that the Names of the Inventors were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40984:40"/>upon the things invented by them, as appears by that Comical Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion [<hi>Without</hi> Ceres <hi>and</hi> Bacchus, Venus <hi>is a cold</hi>] Which in other terms is no more than this, That <hi>without good Meat and Drink Luſt languiſheth. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the Great in a famous Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe which he writes to his Mother, tells her, That the dread of his Power had ſo far wrought upon a Prieſt, as to make him diſcover to him this great Secret and Myſtery, that the <hi>Gods</hi> were but Men. In which Diſcourſe he makes <hi>Vulcan</hi> the firſt of all the <hi>Gods,</hi> and after him the Race of <hi>Jupiter.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Story of <hi>Iſis,</hi> and the ſcatter'd members and empty Tomb of thy <hi>Serapis</hi> or <hi>Oſiris;</hi> and laſtly, their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Rites and Myſteries, and you'l find them made up of the diſmal Events, Deaths, Funerals, Mourning and Wail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of theſe caitive <hi>Gods Iſis</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the <hi>Dog's-Head-Idol,</hi> and her bald <hi>Prieſts,</hi> mourns for, laments and ſeeks her loſt Son, and her miſerable Worſhippers beat their breaſts, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and imitate the ſorrow of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40984:41"/>Mother; and ſoon after you ſee <hi>Iſis</hi> by and by overjoy'd for having found her Little-One; her <hi>Prieſts</hi> are merry, and the <hi>Dog</hi>'s ſnout triumphs for the feat he has done in finding him. Thus they fail not punctually every year to loſe what they have found, and then to find again what they have loſt. Now I pray you, what can be more ridiculous, than to bewail that which we worſhip, or to worſhip that which we bewail? And yet ſuch fop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries as theſe, which formerly were the Religion of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> are now (forſooth) become the Devotions of the <hi>Romans. Ceres</hi> with lighted torches in her hands, and Serpents twiſting about them, ſeeks her Daughter <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerpina,</hi> full of languiſhing care and trouble, who having ſtray'd too far, was ſtoln away and raviſh'd by <hi>Pluto.</hi> This is the ſum and ſubſtance of the <hi>Eleuſinian</hi> Myſteries: And the Rites uſed in the Worſhip of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> are no leſs ridiculous. He is ſuckled by a She goat, for want of a better Nurſe, and the poor Infant is ſtoln away from
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40984:41"/>his Father, for fear he ſhould devour him; the <hi>Corybantes</hi> in the mean while ſoundly plying their Cymbals, to drown the cryes of the Bantling, from coming to the ears of his more than inhumane Father. I am aſham'd to relate the Account they give of <hi>Cybele,</hi> how ſhe gelded <hi>Atys,</hi> and made him an Eunuch-God, becauſe ſhe could not tempt him to commit Adultery with her, who was old and ugly, having been the Mother of ſo many <hi>Gods.</hi> And therefore, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to this Story, her <hi>Prieſts</hi> volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily geld themſelves, to the end they might be capable of that Dignity. I leave you to judge, whether theſe be not real miſeries, rather than Religious Myſteries. Come we now to ſpeak of the goodly form, meen and accou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trements of your <hi>Gods;</hi> than which, what can be more ſhameful and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous? <hi>Vulcan</hi> is a limping crazy <hi>God. Apollo,</hi> though he has liv'd ſo many Ages, is ſtill a beardleſs Boy; whereas his Son <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> has a fair and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Beard. <hi>Neptune</hi>'s Eyes are blue;
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:40984:42"/>
               <hi>Minerva</hi>'s gray; <hi>Juno</hi> has Ox-Eyes; <hi>Pan</hi>'s Feet are garniſh'd with claws; <hi>Saturn</hi>'s are charg'd with fetters, and <hi>Mercury</hi>'s fledg'd with Wings. <hi>Janus</hi> has two faces, as if he would go back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and forward at once. <hi>Diana</hi> the Huntreſs has her Garments tuck'd up to her thighs; but She at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> is in a manner made up all of paps: As ſhe is the Goddeſs of Hell, they give her three Heads, and good ſtore of Arms and Hands. Yea, your <hi>Jupiter</hi> himſelf ſometimes has a Beard of much gravity, and at other times has a Chin as bare as my hand. When he has the Sirname of <hi>Hammon,</hi> he wears horns; when that of <hi>Capitolinus,</hi> he is arm'd with Thunder-bolts; when that of <hi>Latiaris,</hi> he is all beſmear'd with blood; and when that of <hi>Feretrius,</hi> he is very ſtill and quiet. And not to go over the many ſeveral <hi>Jupiters,</hi> there being as many Monſters of him, as there are Names. <hi>Erigone</hi> hangs her ſelf; and the Merit of Self-murther hath advanc'd her to ſhine a perpetual Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin among the Stars. <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lux</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:40984:42"/>dye and live by turns. <hi>Aeſculapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> is ſtruck down with a Thunderbolt, that with the greater Ceremony he may riſe up a <hi>God:</hi> And <hi>Hercules</hi> muſt burn himſelf upon Mount <hi>Octa,</hi> to get rid of his Humanity. Theſe are the fine Stories, which we learn from our ignorant Fore-fathers; and, what is worſe, make them the ſubject of our Studies, and a great piece of Learning. In theſe the <hi>Poets</hi> excel all others, and have by their Authority done vaſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to the Truth; So that <hi>Plato</hi> was much in the right, when he baniſh'd <hi>Homer</hi> (that renown'd, celebrated and crown'd <hi>Poet</hi>) out of his Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. For it is he chiefly, who in his Poem of the <hi>Trojan</hi> Wars, has made a mock of the <hi>Gods,</hi> by mingling them ſo familiarly in the actions and affairs of Men. He brings them in fighting together; He wounds <hi>Venus;</hi> He fetters and binds <hi>Mars,</hi> wounds him and puts him to flight: He make <hi>Briareus</hi> to reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue <hi>Jupiter</hi> out of the hands of the reſt of the <hi>Gods,</hi> when they were conſpiring to bind him to his good behaviour;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:40984:43"/>and repreſents him lamenting the death of his Son <hi>Sarpedon,</hi> as not being able to prevent it. He deſcribes him em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing his <hi>Juno</hi> with more heat, than he us'd to do his belov'd Miſtreſſes, being inflam'd with <hi>Venus</hi>'s Girdle. <hi>Hercules</hi> is made a Scavenger, and cleanſeth Stables. <hi>Apollo</hi> turns Cow-herd to <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metus. Neptune</hi> binds himſelf as a Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labourer to <hi>Laomedon,</hi> to build up the Walls of <hi>Troy,</hi> and is ſo unhappy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, as not to be paid for his drudgery. <hi>Aeneas</hi>'s Armour, and <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-bolt are both hammer'd out upon one and the ſame Anvil; as if Heaven and its Thunders had not been long before <hi>Jupiter</hi> was born in <hi>Crete;</hi> or as if the <hi>Cyclopſes</hi> could have made thoſe affrighting flaſhes, which <hi>Jupiter</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf could not chooſe but be afraid of. What ſhall I ſay of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> being caught in the very Fact of Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery; or of <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s abominable filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with <hi>Ganymedes,</hi> whom he tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into Heaven? All which Fables were invented on purpoſe to authorize the faults and vices of Men. And it
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:40984:43"/>is with thoſe and ſuch like pleaſing Fictions and Lyes, that the Minds of Youth are corrupted; and being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill'd into them in their tender years, grow up with them to Manhood; So that (which is to be lamented) in their very old Age their Minds continue tainted with theſe ſottiſh Fancies; And yet the truth of theſe Matters, is moſt plain and evident to thoſe who will take the pains to enquire into it. All the Antient Writers (whether <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>Roman</hi>) do unanimouſly aſſert, that <hi>Saturn,</hi> the firſt of the goodly Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Gods,</hi> was but a Man. This, <hi>Nepos</hi> and <hi>Craſſus</hi> do affirm in their Hiſtory; and <hi>Thallus</hi> and <hi>Diodorus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the ſame thing; <hi>viz.</hi> That this <hi>Saturn</hi> for fear of falling into his Son's hands, fled out of <hi>Greece</hi> into <hi>Italy,</hi> where <hi>Janus</hi> receiv'd him into his houſe; and being a <hi>Grecian,</hi> full of ingenuity, and inſtructed in Arts and Sciences, taught thoſe barbarous people ſeveral things; as the forming of the Letters of the Alphabet; coining of Money, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:40984:44"/>making diverſe ſorts of uſeful Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: He call'd the Country <hi>Latium,</hi> as if he had ſaid, an <hi>Hiding-place,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had found there a ſafe retreat to hide and conceal himſelf from the attempts of his Son; and to the end he might have his Memory preſerv'd, he call'd the City from his own Name <hi>Saturnia;</hi> as <hi>Janus</hi> call'd the City built upon the Hill <hi>Janniculus,</hi> by that Name, to reſcue his own from oblivion. You ſee then plainly, that <hi>Saturn</hi> was a Man; for he was fain to flee and hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and was the Father, as well as the Son, of a Man. And whereas they call'd him the Son of Heaven and Earth, it was only becauſe his Original and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage were unknown to the <hi>Italians;</hi> as we are wont to ſay of thoſe that come unexpectedly upon us, that they are dropt from the Skies; and of ſuch whoſe birth is mean and obſcure, that they are the Sons of the Earth. As for <hi>Jupiter,</hi> he Reign'd in <hi>Crete,</hi> after he had baniſh'd his Father from that I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland; there he begot Children, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:40984:44"/>there he was buried: And at this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day they ſhew the Cave which bears his Name, and point you to the Grave where he was interred; yea, and the very Ceremonies they uſe in his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, declare him to have been a Man. It would be to no purpoſe to inſiſt on particulars, and to recount his whole <hi>Genealogy:</hi> It is enough that we have prov'd the Father was Mortal, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince that the ſame Quality was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh'd to all his Poſterity; except you ſuppoſe that they became <hi>Gods</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Death; as by the Perjury of <hi>Proculus, Romulus</hi> was rank'd among the Number of the <hi>Gods;</hi> or as <hi>Juba,</hi> by the unanimous conſent and deſire of the <hi>Africans,</hi> was made a <hi>God;</hi> and as other Kings were Deifi'd by their Subjects, not becauſe they really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd them to be <hi>Gods,</hi> but to give them a more honourable diſcharge from their Soveraignty. Beſides, this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Honour is confer'd upon them againſt their Wills; they deſire to continue Men as they are, and are afraid of being Deify'd; and though
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:40984:45"/>old, are not at all ambitious of that Glory. Wherefore we are not to look for <hi>Gods</hi> among thoſe that dye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Gods</hi> are Immortal; nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe who are born, becauſe they are likewiſe obnoxious to Death. <hi>That</hi> only deſerves the Name of a <hi>Deity</hi> which hath neither Beginning nor End. For if <hi>Gods</hi> were ever born, why are they not ſo ſtill, except you will ſay, that now <hi>Jupiter</hi> is too old, and <hi>Juno</hi> paſt Child-bearing; or that they are of the humour of <hi>Minerva,</hi> who choſe to be an old Maid, rather than a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Or indeed have not thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Deities</hi> ceaſed to procreate, becauſe Men have ceaſed to believe ſuch Stories? Moreover, if the <hi>Gods</hi> could beget Children, and thoſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren muſt needs be Immortal, we ſhould already have had more <hi>Gods</hi> than Men; So that by this time the Heavens would not contain them, nor the Air hold them, nor the Earth bear the vaſt increaſe of them. Let us therefore make no difficulty to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm them to have been Men, of whoſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:40984:45"/>Birth and Death we are ſo fully aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd. Neither need any be far to ſeek for a reaſon why the common people, notwithſtanding all this, do adore and worſhip theſe Conſecrated Images; their fooliſh Minds being decoy'd and allur'd by the Curioſity of thoſe Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieces of Art, their Eyes dazled with the luſtre of the Gold, and the brightneſs of the Silver, and poliſh'd whiteneſs of the Ivory. But if any body will take time to conſider how theſe Figures are made, and with what Inſtruments they are carv'd and fram'd, he will bluſh at his ſtanding in awe of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial, that has been ſo abus'd, cut and mangled by the Work-man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he could make a <hi>God</hi> of it. For if this <hi>God</hi> be of Wood, it may be it is the remnant of a funeral Pile, or Gallows; which they under-prop, cut, plane and make ſmooth. If it be of Silver or Braſs, it may poſſibly be made of an old Kettle, or ſomething worſe; (as it hath often happen'd to one of the Kings of <hi>Egypt</hi>) and then it is molten, beaten, hammer'd and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion'd
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:40984:46"/>on an Anvil; and if of Stone, hew'd, wrought and poliſh'd (it may be) by ſome debauch'd and wicked Fellow. Yet is not the <hi>God,</hi> in the leaſt, ſenſible of all theſe tortures and indignities, offer'd to him at his Birth, no more than he is afterwards of the Honour, which accrues to him by your Conſecration and Worſhip; except you will ſay, that this Stone, Wood or Silver is not yet a <hi>God.</hi> But pray when is it, that the Divinity of it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mences? Behold! it is melted, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion'd and grav'd; but it is not a <hi>God</hi> yet: It is ſolder'd, put together and ſet up; yet ſtill it is no <hi>God:</hi> At laſt it is adorn'd, conſecrated and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip'd; and then at laſt with much adoe it is a <hi>God,</hi> when it hath pleas'd vain Man thus to dedicate it. But how much more truly do the moſt contemptible of Animals and Infects, judge your <hi>Gods!</hi> The Mice, Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows and Kites know very well, that they have no ſenſe at all; they tread and pearch upon them, and were they not driven away by you, they would
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40984:46"/>build their Neſts in their very Mouths; the Spiders cover their faces with their Cobwebs, and make uſe of their heads to faſten their threads at. You wipe, cleanſe and bruſh them, and protect the <hi>Gods,</hi> which your ſelves have made, and yet pretend to fear them. And all this while you don't conſider that <hi>GOD</hi> muſt be known by you, before you can worſhip Him, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderately comply with your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Opinions, and chooſe rather to follow others in their Errors, than credit your own Judgments; and in a word, know not what that is for which you have ſuch an awe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence. Thus by hallowing of <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> you have conſecrated <hi>Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice;</hi> thus your vain Images come to be ſtamp'd with the imaginary ſhape of a <hi>Deity;</hi> thus the <hi>Roman</hi> Superſtition had its riſe, and that vaſt number of <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> wherein there are ſo many which are ſilly and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, and ſo many which deſerve pity and compaſſion. Some run about the Streets ſtark naked in the ſharpeſt
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40984:47"/>cold of Winter; others wear fools<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caps, and carry about antick ſhields in their hands; others lance their own skins, and lead their blind <hi>Gods</hi> a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging about the ſtreets. They have ſome Temples which they may not viſit but once a year, and others which none may ever enter but the <hi>Prieſts</hi> alone: Again, they have ſome that are ſhut up from Women, and others prohibited to Men. They have ſome <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> at which a Slave is not permitted to aſſiſt, without a great crime. Some of your Statues may not be crown'd but by the hands of a Woman, who hath known but one Man; others again, only by ſuch as have had to do with many; and with great devotion you ſearch for the moſt lewd and common Harlot that is to be found, to officiate at your Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things. What ſhall we ſay of thoſe, who ſhed their own blood for a Drink-Offering, and by wounding themſelves, think to procure the favour of the <hi>Gods.</hi> Were it not better for them to be <hi>Prophane,</hi> than to be thus <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious?</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:40984:47"/>And do not they alſo offend <hi>GOD,</hi> inſtead of appeaſing Him, who from a ſtrange Superſtition geld them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; ſince if <hi>GOD</hi> delighted in <hi>Eunuchs,</hi> he could have made them ſo, without the aſſiſtance of Man's cruelty? But indeed, who does not ſee that they are poor diſtracted and crack-brain'd men, who act theſe follies; which have nothing to plead for them, but the multitude of thoſe who are engag'd in the ſame Error; as if becauſe this madneſs is Epidemical, it were therefore lawful and juſt too? But you object, that this, which I call Superſtition, has given the <hi>Romans</hi> ſo vaſt an Empire; founded it at firſt, and afterwards rais'd it to that high pitch; they having been always, rather more famous for their Religion and Piety, than for Proweſs and Valour. Well may they boaſt of the remarkable inſtances of their Virtue and Juſtice, from the very Cradle and firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of their Empire! Was it not their Crimes that aſſociated them at firſt, and their Cruelty afterwards,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40984:48"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:40984:48"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:40984:49"/>that made them dreadful to their Neighbours, and laid the firſt Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Government? For their Country being a Sanctuary and Place of Refuge for all ſorts of Criminals, a great number of Thieves, Traitors, Murtherers, Sacrilegious and Inceſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons were ſoon gather'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and to the end, that he who was their great Captain-General, might excel them all in <hi>Villany,</hi> as he did in <hi>Dignity,</hi> he kill'd his own Brother. Theſe were the auſpicious beginnings of this Holy City. Soon after, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Law of Nature, they ſteal away Maids already promiſed, yea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trothed, and Married Women too, from their own Husbands, and force and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe them; and defend their Crime by warring againſt their Fathers-in-law, and ſhedding the blood of their near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Allies: Than which, what can be thought of more prodigious, more barbarous and as, they preſum'd, ſafe in the confidence of their wickedneſs? Their next work is, to drive their Neighbours out of their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40984:49"/>to deſtroy their Cities, rob their Churches, and defile their Altars; carry them into Captivity, and enrich themſelves by Crimes, and the ſpoils and ruine of others. Theſe were the Maxims and Practice both of <hi>Romulus</hi> and his Succeſſors; So that whatever they have, poſſeſs, and worſhip, is all the purchaſe of bold Robbery. Their Temples are built and adorn'd with the ſpoils they have taken in War, that is, with the ruine of Cities, pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage of <hi>Gods</hi> and <hi>Temples,</hi> and ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their <hi>Prieſts.</hi> What an inſolent piece of mockery is this, to eſtabliſh thoſe Religious <hi>Rites,</hi> you have ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly prophan'd, and to worſhip thoſe <hi>Gods,</hi> who were once your Captives? For to pay Adoration to that which you have taken in War, is not ſo much a conſecrating of <hi>Deities,</hi> as an hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Sacriledge.</hi> Indeed all the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs of the <hi>Romans</hi> were but ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny horrid Impieties, and all their Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies, ſo many Sacriledges. It is not therefore the Religion of the <hi>Romans,</hi> that has made them ſo great, as the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40984:50"/>impunity of their Villanies. For how can it be thought, that thoſe <hi>Gods</hi> ſhould favour them in their Wars, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom they took Arms; and which they did not worſhip, till they had firſt led them in Triumph? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, what could thoſe <hi>Gods</hi> do for the <hi>Romans,</hi> who had not been able to do any thing againſt them, either in defence of themſelves, or their people? For as for their own <hi>Country-Gods,</hi> they are well known what they were. <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus, Picus, Tiberinus, Conſus, Pilum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and <hi>Picunnus,</hi> were all Worſhipful <hi>Roman Gods;</hi> And beſides theſe, <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> was the firſt that made and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp'd <hi>Cloacina</hi> (with reverence be it ſpoken) for a <hi>Goddeſs. Hoſtilius</hi> built <hi>Temples</hi> to <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Paleneſs;</hi> and ſoon after, I don't know who rear'd an <hi>Altar</hi> to the <hi>Goddeſs Ague.</hi> In theſe Superſtitions was <hi>Rome</hi> nurs'd up, and taught to worſhip Diſeaſes and Indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of health! And thoſe two pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute Harlots, <hi>Flora</hi> and <hi>Acca Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia,</hi> whom they rank among their <hi>Divinities,</hi> may very well be reckon'd
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40984:50"/>alſo among their <hi>Maladies.</hi> And yet theſe forſooth are the <hi>Gods,</hi> that have enlarg'd the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, and van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh'd the <hi>Gods</hi> of other Nations; for it would be madneſs to ſuppoſe, that <hi>Mars</hi> the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Thracia, Jupiter</hi> of <hi>Crete, Juno</hi> the <hi>Goddeſs</hi> of <hi>Argos, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos</hi> and <hi>Carthage; Diana</hi> of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Scythia,</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> of the <hi>Gods,</hi> and the <hi>Deities,</hi> or rather Monſters, of <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſhould ever help the <hi>Romans</hi> againſt their own people, who for ſo many years had been their conſtant Worſhippers. But it may be they were willing to make this Change, becauſe at <hi>Rome</hi> the <hi>Prieſts</hi> are more Holy, and the Sacred <hi>Virgins</hi> more Chaſt than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny where elſe? Very likely; when for the moſt part thoſe have ſuffer'd the puniſhment of Inceſt, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted it leſs cautiouſly; whereas the reſt eſcaped, not by their being leſs criminal, but by having better hap in the concealing of their lewdneſs. And as for the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> where do they play the Whore-maſters more, than in the Temples and before the Altars? Here
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40984:51"/>they exerciſe the function of Pimps and Panders, and deſign and contrive Adulteries: Neither does Luſt and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery abound ſo much in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Stews, as in their Veſtries and Cells. But beſides, were there not other great Empires and States flouriſhing before theſe Superſtitions were invented, or ſo much as thought-of? As the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrians, Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians, Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and <hi>Egyptians,</hi> though they had no <hi>Pontifs,</hi> nor that rabble of <hi>Arvales</hi> and <hi>Salii, Veſtals</hi> and <hi>Augurs;</hi> nor no Chickens religiouſly penn'd up, from whoſe feeding, or refuſing their Meat, all meaſures were taken, and the greateſt Affairs of ſtate determin'd. But let's come now to thoſe <hi>Auguries</hi> and <hi>Divinations</hi> by the flight or chattering of Birds, which the <hi>Romans</hi> ſo religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly obſerv'd, and the neglect or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of which (as you took notice) has prov'd as fatal, as the heeding of the ſame has been fortunate Was it becauſe the moſt ſolemn dancing of the Barley peckt by the Chickens, was not waited for, that the Armies of <hi>Clodius,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40984:51"/>Junius</hi> and <hi>Flaminius</hi> were defeated? But what ſhall we ſay then of <hi>Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> who religiouſly obſerv'd all theſe, and yet was taken by the Enemy? and ſo did <hi>Mancinus;</hi> and for all that, was forced to ſurrender himſelf upon diſhonourable terms. <hi>Paulus</hi>'s Chick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens fed heartily at the Battel of <hi>Cannae,</hi> yet he periſh'd, and the greateſt part of the Commonwealth with him. And though <hi>Caeſar</hi> made ſlight of the <hi>Auguries</hi> that forbad him to go into <hi>Africa</hi> before Winter, yet had he a ſucceſsful Voyage, and return'd Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror; ſo that his contempt of theſe fopperies did but ſeem to favour his Paſſage and Victory. Now as to the <hi>Oracles,</hi> how many things might not I have to ſay concerning them? <hi>Amphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>araus</hi> after his death foretells future e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents to others, who when alive could not foreſee the treachery of his Wife againſt him, for a Bracelet of Gold. <hi>Tireſias</hi> the blindman propheſies things to come, and yet is not aware of what is preſent. <hi>Ennius</hi> in behalf of <hi>Pyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhus</hi> counterfeits the Anſwers of <hi>Apollo,</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:40984:52"/>ſeeing he was become ſpeechleſs; whoſe wary and ambiguous <hi>Oracle</hi> was ſilenc'd as ſoon as Men began to be more wiſe and leſs credulous. Thus <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> was not afraid to accuſe the <hi>She-Prieſts</hi> of <hi>Apollo</hi> of giving ſuch anſwers as <hi>Philip</hi> would have her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well acquainted with thoſe Holy jugglings. But what? Will you then deny that <hi>Oracles</hi> and <hi>Auguries</hi> ever hit the truth? Well, ſuppoſe we grant it: Pray what will it avail to the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of <hi>Oracles,</hi> if among ſo many lies one true word has, at a venture, been delivered; or that <hi>Chance</hi> has, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, imitated <hi>Deſign.</hi> But give me leave to go back to the Spring, from whence theſe Errors flow, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Deep, from which ſuch groſs darkneſſes do iſſue forth. There are certain impure and vagrant Spirits, who being loaden with Earthly pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and deſires have ſunk themſelves down to this lower Orbe, from their Original Station: and thoſe miſerable wretches having thus loſt the Natural advantages wherewith they were cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:40984:52"/>and having given up themſelves to all manner of Vices, they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to comfort themſelves under this calamity, by bringing others into the ſame miſery; for as they have cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted themſelves, ſo do they delight in nothing more than to corrupt others; and as they have ſeparated themſelves from <hi>GOD,</hi> ſo do they their utmoſt endeavours by falſe ways, Religions and Superſtition, to keep Mankind eſtranged from Him. Theſe <hi>Spirits,</hi> the <hi>Poets</hi> acknowledge to be <hi>Daemons;</hi> concerning whoſe Nature the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> maintain ſeveral Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes; and they were very well known to <hi>Socrates,</hi> who had one of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways attending him, according to whoſe intimations, he either under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took or declin'd all buſineſs. The <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians</hi> alſo are very well acquainted with this ſort of <hi>Spirits,</hi> by whoſe help they do all thoſe ſtrange Feats, and Juggling tricks, by which they make us believe, we ſee that which is not, or not to ſee, that which really is; and in a word atchieve to our
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:40984:53"/>great amazement all thoſe extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and aſtoniſhing Wonders that are ſpoken of. Nevertheleſs <hi>Hoſtanes,</hi> who was the <hi>Chiefeſt</hi> of all theſe <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians,</hi> both in word and deed, gives <hi>GOD</hi> the Honour due to Him, and ſays that the Angels are his Miniſters and Meſſengers, who adore Him with fear and trembling; To which he adds, that the <hi>Daemons</hi> are Earthly and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabond <hi>Spirits,</hi> that hate Mankind. And <hi>Plato,</hi> who found it a hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to know <hi>GOD,</hi> did not find it ſo, to know them. He ſpeaks both of <hi>Daemons</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> and in his <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogue</hi> call'd the <hi>BANQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ET,</hi> he endeavours to explain the Nature of the former; ſaying, That they are of a <hi>Middle</hi> ſubſtance between <hi>Mortal</hi> and <hi>Immortal,</hi> that is, between a <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Spirit;</hi> being made of a mixture of Terreſtrial groſneſs, and Celeſtial purity. By which means they have an eaſie acceſs to us, to ſtir up our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, and by conveighing themſelves into our hearts, to affect our Senſes, raiſe our Paſſions, and kindle in our
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:40984:53"/>Souls the flames of Luſt. Theſe <hi>Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> then, who are mix'd and impure <hi>Spirits,</hi> as we have plainly demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Authority of <hi>Wiſemen, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers,</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> himſelf, lurk pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately in thoſe Statues and Images, which are conſecrated unto them; and by their <hi>Enthuſiaſms</hi> get ſo great an Authority over the minds of men, as of preſent <hi>Deities;</hi> and this, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring their <hi>Prophets,</hi> dwelling in their Temples; by animating and acting the Entrails of Beaſts; by directing the flying of Birds, determining of Lots, and uttering <hi>Oracles,</hi> which are generally obſcure, and mixt with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of lyes; for they both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive others, and are deceiv'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; who as they do not know the Truth fully, ſo they oft conceal, and will not confeſs that which they do know, becauſe it tends to their own ſhame and confuſion. Thus they make it their buſineſs to depreſs, and ſink us downwards from Heaven to Earth, and to eſtrange us from <hi>GOD,</hi> by immerſing us into Matter; They
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:40984:54"/>trouble and diſquiet our life, moleſt us with Dreams; and this by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage they have, as <hi>Spirits,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey themſelves into our Bodies; where they counterfeit Diſeaſes, terrifie our Minds, diſtort our Members, thereby to oblige us to adore them; and that after they are glutted with the reaking ſteam of Altars, and the blood of ſlain Beaſts, by undoing their own Charms, the honour of Healing might be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to them. They are theſe very <hi>Spirits,</hi> which act thoſe raging mad folks, whom you ſee running along the ſtreets, and who are every whit as much <hi>Prophets,</hi> as thoſe who give an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers in your <hi>Temples;</hi> for they both foame, rage, and are whirl'd about a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like: Indeed they are <hi>Daemons</hi> which poſſeſs the one, as well as the other, with this only difference, that the object of their madneſs does vary. From the ſame alſo proceed all thoſe deluſions, you even now rehears'd, as that of <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s commanding in a Dream that his Games ſhould be reſtor'd; the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> on
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:40984:54"/>Horſeback, and that of a Ship being tow'd along by the girdle of a <hi>Roman</hi> Matron. The moſt now adays, and among them many of your own Party, know very well, that the <hi>Devils</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves do oft confeſs all theſe things, when by the torture of our Words, and the Fire of our Prayers, they are driven out and diſpoſſeſs'd. Then it is that <hi>Saturn, Serapis</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> with all the Crew of <hi>Gods</hi> you worſhip, being overcome with anguiſh, do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare plainly what they are; nor have they the power by lying, to conceal their own ſhame (as you may be ſure they fain would) though ſome of their deluded Adorers be preſent. Sure you will credit the teſtimony of your own <hi>Gods,</hi> when they witneſs the Truth againſt themſelves, and confeſs they are Devils. For when thoſe Wretches are conjur'd to come forth by the Name of the <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Only GOD,</hi> they tremble and quake within the Bodies they have poſſeſs'd, and either leap forth preſently, or vaniſh by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, according as the Faith of the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:40984:55"/>Patient, and Grace of the Ghoſtly Phyſician are ſtronger or weaker; So that they dread the nearneſs of thoſe <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> whom at a diſtance, by your means, they trouble and diſturb in their Aſſemblies; and to that end inſinuate themſelves into the hearts of the ſimple and ignorant, and there ſow the ſeeds of hatred againſt our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: For nothing is more natural, than to hate thoſe whom we dread, and give all the trouble we can, to thoſe of whom we ſtand in awe. So they prepoſſeſs and prejudice the hearts of men againſt us, that they begin to hate us, before they know us; leſt knowing us, without this prejudice, they might deſire to imitate, or at leaſt not be able to condemn us. Now how unjuſt it is to paſs a Judgment upon things which one knows not, as you do in condemning us, you may take warning from us, who do ſo heartily repent for having committed the ſame fault; for we were once as you are, and had the ſame Sentiments, being involv'd in the ſame blindneſs
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:40984:55"/>and ſtupidity of Error, when we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd that the <hi>Chriſtans</hi> worſhip'd Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, devour'd Children, defil'd their Feaſts with Inceſts; without conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that though ſuch things were commonly reported, yet they never were prov'd, and that none all this while has ever confeſs'd the leaſt tittle of any one of theſe Crimes, though beſides the aſſurance of Pardon, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eward of ſuch a diſcovery might have been a great temptation thereunto. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndeed to be a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> is ſo far from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mplying any thing that is evil or cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, that they who are convict, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>her bluſh at it, nor fear the puniſhment which attends it: No, you ſee them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lory in it, and troubled at nothing but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat they were ſo no ſooner. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heleſs we our ſelves, at the ſame time when we undertook the Defence of <hi>Parricides,</hi> and perſons guilty of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and Inceſt, would not ſo much as hear the Plea that <hi>Chriſtians</hi> were ready to make for themſelves, whom we ſometimes made endure a cruel corture, not out of hatred, but pity,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:40984:56"/>forſooth, that by conſtraining them through the greatneſs of torments to renounce their Religion, we might ſave their lives: Oh! perverſe Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, to make uſe of the Rack, not to force the ſufferer to declare the Truth, but to deny it. Now if it ſo happened that any one, leſs conſtant, being overcome with the pains of thoſe tortures, did renounce his Religion, he was received into favour, as if by ſuch an abjuration, he had made atonement for all the Crimes, which are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charg'd upon them. By which you may plainly ſee, that we formerly were of the ſame mind and perſuaſion with you, doing the very ſame things as you do now. But indeed, had you been govern'd by <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and not by the inſtigation of <hi>Evil Spirits,</hi> your buſineſs would have been to have urg'd the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> not to renounce their Religion; but to confeſs their Inceſts, Whoredoms, impious Ceremonies, and their Sacrificing of Infants; which are the fabulous Stories wherewith the ſame <hi>Daemons</hi> have fill'd the ſilly peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:40984:56"/>Minds, to make them deteſt and abhor us. But no wonder if all theſe horrid lyes and Fictions do vaniſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way before the appearance of Truth, which thoſe Monſters ſo much op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, making it their buſineſs to ſpread and foment falſe reports. From theſe alſo that Fable had its riſe, That we worſhip an <hi>Aſſe</hi>'s Head. But, I pray you, who can be conceiv'd ſo much a fool, to worſhip ſuch a thing; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who is ſo much a fool as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve we do it, except thoſe who are guilty of as extravagant and impious Devotions themſelves? For indeed it is you make both <hi>Aſſes</hi> and Stables Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by having conſecrated your <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs Hippona,</hi> and given her the Charge over them; and when you celebrate the ſolemn <hi>Rites</hi> of your <hi>Goddeſs Iſis,</hi> you, with a great deal of <hi>Ceremony,</hi> adorn that <hi>Animal:</hi> Yea, you pay Adoration to the heads of <hi>Oxen</hi> and <hi>Rams;</hi> ſo that you <hi>Worſhip</hi> the ſame Beaſts, which you <hi>Sacrifice.</hi> Some of your <hi>Gods</hi> are made up of a mixt ſhape of <hi>Goats</hi> and <hi>Men,</hi> and others of them
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:40984:57"/>have the Heads half of <hi>Dogs</hi> and half of <hi>Lyons.</hi> Don't you with the <hi>Egyti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> worſhip and feed an <hi>Ox</hi> under the Name of <hi>Apis?</hi> Neither do you diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow the worſhip of their other goodly <hi>Deities;</hi> as <hi>Serpents, Crocodiles,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Beaſts, Birds</hi> and <hi>Fiſhes;</hi> ſo that it is accounted <hi>Capital,</hi> to kill any one of theſe <hi>Gods.</hi> Are there not a great many amongſt you, who with the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians,</hi> ſtand as much in awe of the biting ſharpneſs of an Onion, as of their <hi>Goddeſs Iſis,</hi> and are as much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of the noiſe of breaking wind backward, as of their <hi>God Serapis?</hi> As for ſuch as accuſe us of adoring the privy Parts of our <hi>Prieſts,</hi> they do but charge us with their own Villanies; for ſuch filthy Devotions are very ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to thoſe debauched and lewd peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, among whom 'tis but too common for both Sexes, to proſtitute all their Members, and who give the name of Courteſie and kindneſs to the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant Obſcenity and Laſciviouſneſs; who envy the liberty of Strumpets, and commit ſuch unnatural filthineſs
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:40984:57"/>with one another, as no modeſt Tongue can expreſs, or Pen ſet down; and who ſooner grow weary, than aſham'd of their impudent laſciviouſneſs. Oh horrible lewdneſs! They willingly ſuffer thoſe things to be committed upon themſelves, which neither tender age is able to bear, nor the baſeſt of ſlaves will yield to. As for our part, we are ſo far from being guilty of ſuch filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy actions, that we do even bluſh at the bare recital of them; and indeed, I ſhould think my ſelf to tranſgreſs the bounds of Civility, ſhould I inſiſt any longer upon this Matter, though it be in order to defend our Religion. For really you accuſe us, who are Chaſt and Modeſt, of ſuch Crimes, as we could not have believed there had been ſuch, had there not been the proofs of them from among your ſelves. As to that which you ſay, that we worſhip a wicked Perſon and his Croſs, you are greatly miſtaken; for how could he have deſerv'd to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp'd, had he been an Evil-doer; or to be believ'd a <hi>GOD,</hi> had he been
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40984:58"/>only Earthly? He is ſurely very miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, who repoſes all his confidence in a mortal man, ſince all hopes of his help dye with him. The <hi>Egyptians</hi> indeed are guilty of this folly, who chuſe a Man for the Object of their Worſhip, whom they pray unto; conſult upon all occaſions, and to whom they offer Sacrifice. But all this while, whether he will or no, he that is a <hi>God</hi> to others, is but a <hi>Man</hi> to himſelf, and though he may deceive others, he cannot deceive his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Upon Kings and great Perſons alſo baſe flattery has beſtow'd the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Gods;</hi> whereas it had been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to have paid them their due honours; though to ſpeak the truth, Honour is properly due only to thoſe who are eminently deſerving, as Love is to excellently good Men. Thus they invoke theſe Divine Powers, they pray before their Images, implore the help of their <hi>Genii,</hi> that is, their <hi>Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> and hold it a leſs Crime for a Man to be perjur'd when he ſwears by <hi>Jupiter,</hi> than when he ſwears by the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:40984:58"/>Emperor's <hi>Genius.</hi> We neither wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Croſſes, nor wiſh to be nail'd to them. You your ſelves are more likely to adore them, who worſhip Wooden <hi>Gods,</hi> that are made of the ſame Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And what are your Banners and Standards, but gilt and beautified Croſſes? Nay, the very Trophies of your Victories do not only bear the figure of a Croſs, but of a Crucified Man. Indeed the Sign of the Croſs is naturally repreſented in many things, as in a Ship, when under Sail, or when row'd with Oars; alſo when a Man prays to <hi>GOD</hi> with his hands ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth, he makes the ſame Figure; So that the Figure of the Croſs, has both a ground in <hi>Natural Reaſon,</hi> and in your <hi>Religion,</hi> as being form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the moſt Solemn action of it, Prayer.</p>
            <p>NOW I would fain meet with that Man, that ſays, or believes, that the blood of a murther'd Infant, is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itiating <hi>Ceremony</hi> of our Religion. Firſt, who could have the heart to ſhed the blood of a young Innocent, that
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:40984:59"/>is but newly born? Surely none can imagine or believe ſuch a Crime, but he who can commit it. 'Tis you that expoſe your Children, new-born, to wild Beaſts and Birds, and ſtrangle them at their coming into the World: Nay, there are ſome among you, who by taking Potions, to cauſe abortion, deſtroy them in the Womb, and are guilty of their death, even before they are born. Which cruelty you have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of your <hi>Gods;</hi> For <hi>Saturn</hi> was not contented to expoſe his own Children, but devour'd them himſelf: Upon which account they were us'd in ſome parts of <hi>Africa</hi> to offer him ſuch little Infants, whom they prevented from crying, by ſtopping their mouths with kiſſes, that they might not ſacrifice ſad and mournful Victims to their <hi>Gods.</hi> It was alſo a Cuſtom among the <hi>Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> to ſacrifice Strangers that lodg'd with them; which a King of <hi>Egypt</hi> alſo practis'd. The <hi>Gauls</hi> ſacrificed hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, or rather inhumane, Offerings to <hi>Mercury.</hi> The <hi>Roman</hi> Prieſts have up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome occaſions overwhelm'd and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:40984:59"/>buried a <hi>Grecian</hi> Man and Woman, as likewiſe a Man and Woman of <hi>Gaul,</hi> alive: And at this day the ſolemn Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip paid to <hi>Jupiter Latiaris,</hi> is cutting of a Man's throat; which, indeed, very well becomes <hi>Saturn</hi>'s Son, thus to gorge himſelf with the blood of a Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal. From whence, I ſuppoſe, it was, that <hi>Catiline</hi> learn'd to ratifie his Conſpiracy with humane blood; and that <hi>Bellona</hi> does ſtill oblige thoſe to drink a draught of it, who conſecrate themſelves to her ſervice. With which bloody Medicine, a thouſand times worſe than the Diſeaſe, the Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-ſickneſs is alſo cured. Nor are they much leſs barbarous, who from the Amphitheatre take and eat wild Beaſts, all beſmear'd with blood, and newly fed with the fleſh and entrails of Men. For our part, it is not lawful for us, either to ſee or hear of Murthers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; and ſo much do we abhor Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane blood, that we eat not even that of Beaſts. As for our inceſtuous and promiſcuous Feaſts, it is a Calumny in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented at a conſultation of Devils, on
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:40984:60"/>purpoſe to obſcure the glory of our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, and deter Men from our Religion, before they had try'd it, by the horror of ſo great a Crime; and what your <hi>Orator Fronto</hi> has ſaid concerning it, is rather an <hi>Invective</hi> than an <hi>Evidence.</hi> But, really, it's your ſelves, that are guilty of Inceſts, and not we. The <hi>Perſians</hi> marry their own Mothers; the <hi>Egyptians</hi> and the <hi>Athenians,</hi> their Siſters. Your Stories and Tragedies, wherein you take ſo much delight, boaſt of Inceſts; and ſo you worſhip <hi>Gods,</hi> who have committed Inceſt with their own Mothers, Daughters, and Siſters. 'Tis therefore no wonder that that Vice is ſo frequent and faſhionable amongſt you, ſince your very <hi>Gods</hi> are your encouraging Examples and Complices. And indeed, it is no ſtrange thing, if oft at unawares you commit In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt, by your whoring indifferently e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where, and by expoſing your Children to the mercy of others; ſo that it cannot well be ſuppoſed, but that you ſometimes light upon them. Thus you ſee that whilſt you accuſe us of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:40984:60"/>feign'd Inceſts, you are guilty of real ones your ſelves. But <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are not wont to make an outward ſhew of their Chaſtity; but enſhrine it in their Minds, and do not ſtudy ſo much to ſeem chaſt, as to be really ſo. All of us have either one only wedded Wife, or no Woman at all. As for our <hi>Feaſts,</hi> they are not only Chaſt, but Sober; for we do not ſpend our time in over-charging our ſtomachs with Meat and Drink; but we tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the joys of our Feaſts with the gravity and ſeriouſneſs of our Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. And as we are thus Chaſt in our Aſſemblies, ſo are we no leſs ſuch every where elſe. There are many amongſt us, who keep themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defil'd and holy in an unmarried ſtate, without boaſting of it; and we are ſo far from being inceſtuous perſons, that ſome of us are even aſham'd of lawful pleaſures. As for what concerns Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, it doth not follow, that becauſe we decline your Purple and Dignities, that therefore we are of the dregs of the people; nor are we to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:40984:61"/>Factious, if we all aſpiring after the ſame felicity keep company with one another, and all meet together as peaceably as we behave our ſelves ſingly and alone. Nor ought we to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus'd for prating in corners, if you be either aſham'd or afraid to hear us in publick. And if our Number daily increaſes, it is not our Crime, but our Commendation; an excellent courſe of life, is not only apt to engage thoſe who are enter'd into it to perſevere and continue in it, but to invite and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure others to it. We do not know one another by any marks we have on our bodies, as you fancy; but by our modeſty and innocency. That we love one another ſo entirely, as you are troubled to ſee it, is, becauſe we know not how to hate. And that we call one another <hi>Brethren,</hi> which you envy us for, is, becauſe we have all <hi>One</hi> and the ſame <hi>Father,</hi> one and the ſame <hi>Faith,</hi> and one and the ſame <hi>Hope.</hi> But for your part, you do not owne one another; you rage with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and hatred againſt one another; and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:40984:61"/>the only ſign of your Brotherhood is Parricide, and your frequent imbruing your hands in the blood of your neareſt Relations. But you ſuppoſe, that we conceal <hi>That</hi> which we worſhip, becauſe we have neither <hi>Temples</hi> nor <hi>Altars.</hi> To what purpoſe ſhould we make any form or repreſentation of <hi>GOD,</hi> whoſe living Image, Man himſelf is? Or what <hi>Temple</hi> ſhould we raiſe to <hi>Him,</hi> ſince this whole <hi>World,</hi> which was made by Him, is not able to contain Him? Or ſhall we Mortals, who live in great Palaces, confine the Incomprehenſible <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>HIS MAJESTY,</hi> to the narrow compaſs of ſome <hi>Temple</hi> or <hi>Chappel?</hi> Were it not much better to dedicate our <hi>Mind</hi> for the place of his <hi>Abode;</hi> and conſecrate our <hi>Heart</hi> for his <hi>Altar?</hi> Shall we offer to <hi>GOD</hi> Sacrifices and Oblations of ſuch Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as he has made for our uſe? Would not this look indeed as if we had a mind to reject his Bounty, and to throw back his Gifts into his own Hands; which ſpeaks the greateſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, eſpecially ſince the only ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:40984:62"/>Offering to him, is a good Mind and a pure Heart, with a ſincere Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. So that he that lives innocently, prays to <hi>GOD</hi> acceptably; he that deals juſtly, preſents <hi>Him</hi> with an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of a ſweet ſavour; he who ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtains from fraud, doth moſt effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly propitiate and atone the <hi>Deity;</hi> and he that reſcues a Man that is in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his life, does kill the fatteſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. Theſe are our Sacrifices; theſe are our Myſteries; and with us, he is moſt Devout and Religious, who is moſt Juſt. But you wonder, that we neither can ſhew to others the <hi>GOD</hi> whom we Worſhip, nor ſee him our ſelves. Does this ſeem ſtrange to you? Why, for this very reaſon we do moſt aſſuredly believe <hi>Him</hi> to be <hi>GOD,</hi> becauſe we can perceive <hi>Him,</hi> but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee <hi>Him.</hi> For his omnipotent <hi>Virtue</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> is always preſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, in the Works which he has made, and in the whole courſe of <hi>Nature;</hi> when it thunders, when it lightens, when it is fair; all his works proclaim <hi>Him:</hi> Let it not therefore
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:40984:62"/>ſeem ſtrange to you, that you do not ſee <hi>GOD.</hi> All things are mov'd and driven by the Wind, and yet you ſee it not; And the Sun it ſelf, that makes all things to be ſeen, is in a manner in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, by reaſon of its ſuperlative and dazling brightneſs; inſomuch as ſhould we gaze long, and ſtedfaſtly fix our eyes on it, it would blind them, and put them out. And canſt thou think thy ſelf able to bear the ſight of his Glory, who made the Sun, and is the <hi>Fountain</hi> of all <hi>Light,</hi> when thou art afraid of his <hi>Lightnings,</hi> and hideſt thy ſelf from his <hi>Thunder?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, wouldſt thou ſee <hi>GOD</hi> with thy Eyes of fleſh, when thou canſt neither ſee nor take hold of thine own Soul, by which thou doſt live and ſpeak? But perhaps you will ſay, <hi>GOD</hi> is ignorant of what we do, and <hi>He</hi> being in Heaven, can neither conſider all, nor take knowledge of every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon and his concernments. How greatly are you miſtaken? For how can <hi>He</hi> be far from any of us, when all things in <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:40984:63"/>and in the immenſe ſpace beyond them, are full of <hi>Him,</hi> and known to <hi>Him. He</hi> is not only with us, but within us; And as the <hi>Sun,</hi> though fixed in the <hi>Heavens,</hi> yet diffuſes it ſelf through the whole <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe,</hi> is preſent every where, and mingles its light with every thing, without ſtaining its brightneſs; ſo with much more reaſon, can <hi>nothing</hi> be hid from, or ſecret to <hi>GOD,</hi> the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Beholder</hi> of <hi>all things;</hi> the <hi>Darkneſs</hi> hides not from <hi>Him,</hi> for <hi>He</hi> is there alſo; nor the <hi>thoughts</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> which are the truer <hi>Darkneſs</hi> of the <hi>two.</hi> We live not only under His <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernance,</hi> but, as I may ſay, with <hi>Him.</hi> Neither ought we to preſume upon our great Numbers, as ſuppoſing that one may eaſily eſcape unſeen among ſo vaſt a Multitude; For though we may ſeem to our ſelves a great many, yet are we but a few with reſpect to <hi>GOD.</hi> We, indeed, divide and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh the <hi>Earth</hi> into <hi>Countries</hi> and <hi>Nations;</hi> but to <hi>GOD</hi> this whole <hi>World</hi> is but one <hi>Houſe. Kings</hi> cannot acquaint themſelves with the State and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:40984:63"/>Concerns of their own <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> without the Eyes of many Miniſters; but the <hi>MONARCH</hi> of the whole <hi>World</hi> needs none to inform <hi>Him;</hi> we being not only under his Eye, but even in his <hi>Boſom.</hi> You ſay, it avail'd nothing to the <hi>Jews,</hi> that they worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped <hi>One</hi> Only <hi>GOD,</hi> with <hi>Temples, Altars,</hi> and a vaſt Number of <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies;</hi> but in this you miſtake through ignorance, if either not remembring, or not knowing the Hiſtory of former times, you take notice only of ſome latter Events: For whilſt they ador'd our <hi>GOD</hi> holily, religiouſly and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently. (I ſay Our <hi>GOD,</hi> for the ſame is the <hi>GOD</hi> of the whole <hi>World</hi>) whilſt they obey'd his Juſt <hi>Commands</hi> and wholeſome <hi>Laws,</hi> they became of a ſmall Number, a mighty Nation; of <hi>poor,</hi> they were made <hi>rich,</hi> and from a ſtate of <hi>Slavery,</hi> arriv'd to a moſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſant <hi>Monarchy:</hi> A few of them, and unarm'd, put to flight great Armies and overthrew them, the Elements at <hi>God</hi>'s command fighting for them. Look into their own Writings, or if it like
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:40984:64"/>you better, into thoſe of the <hi>Romans;</hi> read what <hi>Joſephus</hi> and <hi>Antonius Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus</hi> (not to mention thoſe Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that were before them) write of that <hi>People,</hi> and you'l find, that their Sins drew down Calamities up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and whatever Evils befell them, were long before propheſied would overtake 'em, in caſe they ſhould ſtill continue in their Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: So that indeed they forſook <hi>GOD,</hi> before they were forſaken of <hi>Him,</hi> and were not (as you impiouſly ſay) taken Captives with their <hi>GOD,</hi> but given up by <hi>Him,</hi> as deſerters of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Law.</p>
            <p>AS to what concerns the general Conflagration of the Univerſe, it is a vulgar Error, to think it a thing diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult or impoſſible that the World ſhould all on the ſudden be ſet on fire, and conſum'd by that means. There is no man doubts, but that which has a Beginning muſt have an End, and that that which is made, muſt finally periſh; That the Heavens themſelves, and all things therein contain'd, as
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:40984:64"/>they had a Beginning, muſt likewiſe have an End; and that ceaſing to be nouriſh'd by the exhalations of freſh and ſalt-waters, they will be inflam'd; for ſo the <hi>Stoicks</hi> ſtedfaſtly believe, that all the moiſture of <hi>Nature</hi> being ſpent, the whole World will preſently take fire: And the <hi>Epicureans</hi> are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of the ſame Opinion, as touching the ruin of the Univerſe, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagration of the Elements. As for <hi>Plato,</hi> he ſaith, That ſome parts of the World are at times drown'd with floods and inundations, others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd by fire; and though he ſaid that it was made ſo at the firſt, as that it might continue for ever; yet he adds, that <hi>GOD, Who</hi> is the <hi>Maker</hi> of it, may deſtroy it when <hi>He</hi> pleaſes. Which is not at all to be wonder'd at, that a Workman can, and may take to pieces his own Work. So that herein you ſee the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> do fully agree with <hi>us;</hi> not that we do follow their ſteps, but they have taken ſome ſhadow of this Truth out of the predictions of our <hi>Prophets,</hi> and have fourbiſh'd and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:40984:65"/>dreſs'd it up after their own way. Thus alſo the moſt renown'd amongſt them, firſt <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> and eſpecially <hi>Plato,</hi> have deliver'd down to us, though very much corrupted and maimed, the Doctrine of another Life after this; for they aſſert, That the Souls of Men after the diſſolution of their bodies, do perpetually remain, and are continually paſſing into new Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; and perverting the Truth ſtill more, they add, That the Souls of Men do return into the bodies of Beaſts and Birds; an Opinion which does more beſeem a <hi>Mountebank</hi> or <hi>Juggler,</hi> than a grave <hi>Philoſopher.</hi> But it is enough for us, that your <hi>Wiſemen</hi> themſelves do in ſome ſort agree with <hi>us.</hi> And who is ſo much a fool, as to deny, that <hi>He</hi> who at firſt made Man, can as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily reſtore and renew him? For as he is nothing after Death, ſo neither was he any thing before Life; And therefore why ſhould we think it ſtrange, that he who at the beginning was made of nothing, ſhould of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing (as to us) be repair'd and reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:40984:65"/>to a new Life; eſpecially ſince it is much more difficult to create a thing which never was, than to reſtore that to its former Being, which has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready been? Or do you believe, that every thing which diſappears to our dull ſight, does periſh in the ſight of <hi>GOD?</hi> Whether the Body moulder into duſt, or be diſſolv'd into water, or be reduc'd to aſhes, or be attenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated into Steam and Air, it is only withdrawn out of our ſight, but to <hi>GOD</hi> it is preſerv'd in the ſeveral E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements into which it is chang'd. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do we fear, as you fancy, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny manner of prejudice comes to our Bodies by Burial; only we obſerve the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> of interring Dead Bodies, as the beſt. Do but look about you, and you'l ſee how, to our comfort, whole <hi>Nature</hi> is a lively Pourtraicture and Repreſentation of our <hi>Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> The Sun riſes and ſets, and ſo do the Stars; Flowers dye and ſpring up again; Trees renew their green Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture every year; and Seeds, unleſs they dye and putrifie in the Earth, do
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:40984:66"/>not return to a new life. And why may not our Bodies, like Trees in Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, hide and preſerve their life and vigour, under a ſeeming withering and deadneſs? Indeed, you cannot expect to ſee this in the depth of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but muſt ſtay till that great Spring comes, which ſhall make our Bodies to flouriſh and live again. Nor am I ignorant that there are very many, who being ſenſible of their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merits, do rather wiſh, than believe, that they ſhall not be after Death; chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the two, rather utterly to be extinguiſh'd, than to be reſtor'd to life again, only to be puniſh'd; which Errour encreaſes daily, by reaſon of the extreme licentiouſneſs of the Age, and the long forbearance of <hi>GOD,</hi> whoſe Judgments the ſlower they are, by ſo much the more juſtly and heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are they laid on at laſt. And yet Men are told both by the Writings of <hi>Wiſemen</hi> and <hi>Poets,</hi> that there is a <hi>Sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian</hi> Lake, and an ever-burning River, prepar'd for the Eternal puniſhment of the Wicked, according to the Oracles
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:40984:66"/>of true <hi>Prophets,</hi> as well as the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the <hi>Daemons</hi> themſelves. Hence it is the <hi>Poets</hi> make <hi>Jupiter</hi> to ſwear by the burning Rivers, and dark Deep; for as he foreſees the torments deſign'd both for himſelf and his worſhippers, ſo does he fear and tremble at them, as being without meaſure, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. For in wonderful wiſe this Fire does both conſume our Bodies and repair them, devour and nouriſh them at once; like the flaſhes of Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which blaſt and kill the body without conſuming it; or thoſe <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cano's</hi> of <hi>Aetna</hi> and <hi>Veſuvius,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that burn continually, without waſting or going out. Thus this infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal penal Fire is ſtrangely fed, without diminution of its Fewel, and preys for ever upon the Bodies of the Damn'd without waſting them. Now, that <hi>GOD</hi> doth deſervedly puniſh them that know him not, impious and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, none but prophane Wretches can deny, ſince it is ſcarce a leſs hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Crime, not to know the <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Lord</hi> of all things, than to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:40984:67"/>and affront <hi>Him.</hi> And although the Ignorance of <hi>GOD,</hi> is enough to make Men lyable to puniſhment, as the true Knowledge of <hi>Him,</hi> doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail for their Pardon and Indemnity; yet if we <hi>Chriſtians</hi> be compar'd with you, notwithſtanding that upon ſome of us our Diſcipline hath leſs ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, we ſhall be found much the Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Men. For you forbid Adulteries, and commit them; whereas we are known as Men, to our Wives alone. You content your ſelves only to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the outward <hi>Act;</hi> whereas with us the very <hi>Thought</hi> of Evil is a Crime. You are afraid that other men ſhould be conſcious of your faults, but we ſtand in awe even of our own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, becauſe we cannot fly nor hide our ſelves from them. The Priſons are crouded with numbers of your own, but you find not one <hi>Chriſtian</hi> there, except he be either a <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> or an <hi>Apoſtate?</hi> Neither let any think to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort himſelf with this, That all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Actions are ſubject to unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Fate</hi> and <hi>Deſtiny:</hi> For though
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:40984:67"/>we attribute ſome Events to <hi>Chance,</hi> yet it is undeniably certain, that the Mind of Man is free in the choice of his Actions, which are therefore only puniſhable and not his Condition. What is Fate, but what <hi>GOD</hi> has ſpoken and decreed concerning every one of us, who being able to foreſee the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of His own Decrees, ſuits them to every ones deſerts and circumſtances; ſo he puniſhes in us, not the Deſtiny of our Nativity, but the ill diſpoſition of our Minds? But no more of this Matter for the preſent; which if it be not ſufficient, we may have occaſion to treat of it more amply another time. Only let me obſerve to you now, that if we are poor (which you are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually upbraiding to us) this is not a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, but an Honor to us; for as the Mind is apt to grow diſſolute by Luxury and Exceſs, ſo is it many times confirm'd in Virtue, by Frugality and a mean Eſtate. And yet how can he be poor who lacks nothing, who co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vets nothing that others have, and who is rich towards <hi>GOD?</hi> He indeed is
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:40984:68"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:40984:68"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:40984:69"/>rather poor, who having much, ſtill co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vets more: And to ſpeak my mind freely, no man is ſo poor by Fortune, as we are all by Nature. The Birds have no Patrimony to live upon, and the Cattel upon a thouſand hills are provided for only from day to day; and we live upon theſe who have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing certain to live upon, for they are all made for us, and we poſſeſs them all, if we covet them not. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as he that travels on the road, is moſt eaſie when he carries leaſt about him; ſo in this journey of life he is happieſt who being eas'd by Poverty, doth not go ſighing under the weight and burthen of Riches, which if we thought needful for us, we might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully beg them of <hi>GOD,</hi> who, no doubt, would not deny us ſomething of that <hi>ALL</hi> which is <hi>His:</hi> But we chuſe rather to deſpiſe riches, than poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs them. Our moſt earneſt <hi>Wiſhes</hi> are for <hi>Innocence;</hi> our moſt fervent <hi>Prayers</hi> for <hi>Patience;</hi> we had much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther live well and vertuouſly with a little, than prodigally and luxuriouſly
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:40984:69"/>with a great Eſtate. When we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go the troubles of this Life, and ſuffer the infirmities of our Nature, we don't ſo much account them pains and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, as a warfare in which we are engaged: For we find that our cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage gains ſtrength from our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and that calamities and afflictions are the uſual Diſcipline of Vertue; it being certain that the vigour of our Bodies, as well as our Minds, is apt to decay for want of exerciſe. Thus all thoſe great Men, whom you magnifie as ſuch Examples of Vertue, became Famous no other way, but by the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and calamities they were exercis'd withall. Neither is it therefore a good conſequence from our ſeeming forlorn condition, to ſay that <hi>GOD</hi> neglects us, or is unable to relieve us; <hi>He</hi> who is the great Governour of all, and the moſt compaſſionate <hi>Lover</hi> of his <hi>Own.</hi> But <hi>He</hi> proves us by adverſities; <hi>He</hi> makes tryal of our temper and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by dangers and ſufferings; <hi>He</hi> ſifts our moſt hidden thoughts and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and to diſcover the bent of our
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:40984:70"/>wills to the utmoſt, <hi>He</hi> calls us to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer death for <hi>Him,</hi> being well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that nothing can periſh in his hands, and miſcarry under his care. In ſhort, as men try <hi>Gold</hi> by fire, ſo does he refine <hi>us</hi> by afflictions. And indeed how delightful a Spectacle muſt it be to <hi>GOD,</hi> to ſee a Chriſtian cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly encountring his pains, and undauntedly preparing himſelf for all manner of threats, puniſhments and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; to ſee him boldly look Death and the Executioner of it in the face, and without the leaſt alteration, to throw himſelf into the devouring flames; to ſee him aſſert his liberty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Kings and Princes, and to yield to none but <hi>GOD,</hi> whoſe <hi>He</hi> is; in a word, like a Conqueror, to triumph over his Judg; for he is really victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, who has obtained what he ſtrives for? Where is the Souldier that would not boldly provoke and challenge dangers in the preſence of his General, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that none but ſuch as give good proof of themſelves, ſhall be rewarded? And yet a General cannot give what
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:40984:70"/>he has not; I mean, he cannot length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en our days, though he may beſtow Honors upon us for our Courage and brave Exploits. But the Souldier of <hi>JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> is ſo far from being abandon'd, even in Death it ſelf, that he triumphs over it, and leads it Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive: So that though he may ſeem to be miſerable, yet he cannot be ſo. You your ſelves exalt, even to the Skies, ſuch as have couragiouſly ſuffer'd for their Country: Witneſs <hi>Mutius Scae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vola,</hi> who being miſtaken in his attempt upon the King, had certainly been put to death by his Enemies, had he not, by a moſt undaunted courage, burnt off his own right hand before their eyes, upon the Altar. And how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are there amongſt us, who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt ſhreaking or crying out, have endur'd, not only to have their right hands, but their whole bodies conſum'd to aſhes, when they might with one word have deliver'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from thoſe extreme tortures? But why do I compare our Men with <hi>Mutius</hi> and <hi>Aquilius</hi> and <hi>Regulus?</hi>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:40984:71"/>Our very Women and Children make ſlight of croſſes and tortures, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concern'd at the ſight of wild and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous Beaſts; and in a word, by a Patience divinely inſpir'd, make a mock of torment in all its frightful ſhapes. And yet ſo miſerably blind are you, as not to conſider that there are none who will either endure tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments without cauſe, or can be ſo courageous under them, without a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural and <hi>Divine</hi> Aſſiſtance. But this is that which perhaps deceives you, That you ſee thoſe who know not <hi>GOD</hi> to abound in <hi>Riches,</hi> flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in <hi>Honor</hi> and excel in <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Dignity.</hi> Poor Wretches! They are lifted up on high, that they may have the greater fall; They are Beaſts fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten'd for Sacrifice, and ſo many Victims crown'd before their Slaughter; ſo that one would think, ſeeing their lewd Lives, that they are ſet upon Thrones, only to abuſe their Power, and to ſin with more licentiouſneſs. Beſides, without the knowledge of <hi>GOD</hi> there can be no ſolid Felicity,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:40984:71"/>ſince all the things of this World are like a Dream, which vaniſhes before we can lay hold of it. Kings feel as many feats in themſelves, as they cauſe in others, and though they are guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a great retinue, yet they are alone in dangers. You are rich (it's true) but it is not well to truſt incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant <hi>Fortune.</hi> Beſides, if things be rightly conſider'd, ſo much Luggage, for ſo ſhort a Journey is more cumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome than uſeful. You glory in your <hi>Purple</hi> and <hi>Dignities;</hi> but without cauſe, ſince Scarlet and rich Veſtments are but a pitiful Ornament to you, if your Souls be tainted with Sin and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with Vice. You pretend to be of a great <hi>Family</hi> and of Noble <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage:</hi> But don't you know that we are all Equal by our Birth, and that Virtue only ought to make the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence among Men. It is therefore with good reaſon that <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who aim at being eſteem'd only upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Virtuous Manners and Modeſt Behaviours, deſpiſe your Shews and Pomps, and fly from them as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:40984:72"/>Inticers and Corrupters of men; and with the ſame reaſon alſo they ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from your Religious <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> as well knowing what was their Beginning and Original. For who can but abhor to hear and ſee thoſe confuſed Conteſts and Shouts of the Multitude at your Chariot-races? What ſober Mind is not aſtoniſh'd to ſee the Art of killing Men, publickly profeſs'd in your <hi>Gladiators</hi> Games? And for your <hi>Theaters,</hi> as the madneſs there is no leſs, ſo they exceed in all manner of infamous lewdneſs and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs; where a bold and ſhameleſs Actor repreſents or relates Adulteries, and the laſcivious Jeſter by making Love, incites to Luſt and Laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; where they diſhonor your <hi>Gods</hi> by aſcribing ſighs and hatred, and Whoredoms, the Paſſions and the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of men to them. With feigned griefs they draw real tears from your eyes; ſo that you can lament perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated Murthers, and take delight in true ones. If we abhor the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of your <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> and of the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:40984:72"/>Wine that has been preſented upon your <hi>Altars,</hi> this is not to be interpreted as an acknowledgment of our fear, but an aſſerting of our juſt liberty. For though nothing can corrupt the Gifts of <hi>GOD,</hi> which <hi>Nature</hi> has produc'd for our uſe, yet we willingly abſtain from thoſe prophane Oblations, leſt we might be thought either to acknowledge the <hi>Daemons,</hi> to whom they are conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or to be aſham'd of our own <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how come you to fancy that we have an Antipathy to Flowers? Don't we gather the Lilly and the Roſe, and whatever the Spring affords, and is eſteem'd either for its beauty or fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grancy? We both ſtrew them, and tye them up into Noſe-gays, and make them into Garlands, which we hang about our necks. But I hope you will excuſe us, if we don't wear Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands on our Heads, and are of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Flowers ought to be ſmelt by the Noſe, and not by the hair or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der part of the Head. Neither do we think it neceſſary to crown the Dead
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:40984:73"/>with Garlands; but wonder at you for doing of it. For what good can Flowers do them, if they have no ſenſe? Or if they have any, why do you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them to the funeral flames? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if they be happy, they do not need them; and if they be miſerable, Flowers will be but a ſmall comfort to them. As for us, we celebrate the Funerals of our Dead Friends with the ſame Modeſty and Compoſedneſs that appears in our whole Life. We don't crown them with Garlands that fade away, they being crown'd with ſuch as are made of immortal and never-dying Flowers, by the hand of <hi>GOD</hi> himſelf. We are moderate in our deſires, being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd of the Bounty of our good <hi>GOD;</hi> and freed from all fear, by the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain hopes of a future Felicity; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimated to do and ſuffer for <hi>Him,</hi> by the Faith of his Glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with us: Inſomuch as we have not only a Happineſs in reverſion at the reſurrection of the Juſt; but are happy already in the contemplation
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:40984:73"/>and proſpect of our future Bleſſedneſs. Therefore let that <hi>Athenian</hi> Droll, <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> enjoy the comfort of his own confeſſion, that he knows nothing, and glory in the deceitful Teſtimony given him by the Oracle, upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; Let <hi>Arceſilas</hi> and <hi>Carneades, Pyrrho,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Academicks</hi> be continually deliberating and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Let <hi>Simonides</hi> for ever ask a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger day for the giving his Anſwer; for our part we do not value thoſe <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> whom we know to have been <hi>Tyrants, Corrupters,</hi> and <hi>Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers,</hi> and who were never more Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, than when they declaim'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their own Vices. We don't en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to make a ſhew of Wiſdom in our Garb, but to have it ſhine forth in the diſpoſition of our Minds and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. We don't talk of great things, but live and do them. In ſhort, we make it our glory to have attain'd that which they ſo earneſtly ſought for, but could never find. Why are we ſo unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to God? Why do we envy our ſelves our own happineſs, that it
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:40984:74"/>ſhould be our lot to ſee the <hi>Divine</hi> Truth come to its full ripeneſs in our days? Let us enjoy this great Bleſſing and advantage of being in the right, and having the Truth on our ſide, with that temper and modeſty which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes us. Let Superſtition be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trol'd; let all impiety be purg'd away, and let the true Religion be preſerv'd and continue for ever.</p>
            <p>WHEN <hi>Octavius</hi> had thus ended his Diſcourſe, we remain'd a good while in a kind of amazement, looking ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly upon one another, without ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one word. For my part I was almoſt tranſported with admiration, that he had both by <hi>Arguments,</hi> and <hi>Examples,</hi> and the <hi>Authority</hi> of Teſtimonies, which his reading furniſh'd him withall, adorn'd ſo good a Cauſe, and ſo clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made out thoſe things which are more eaſily <hi>felt</hi> than <hi>expreſt;</hi> being moſt of all pleas'd to ſee that he had both fought and ſoil'd them at their own Weapons, and clearly demonſtrated, that Truth is not only eaſie, but hath many favourable advantages on its ſide.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:40984:74"/>Whilſt I was thus ſilently muſing with my ſelf, <hi>Caecilius</hi> breaks out into theſe words; I congratulate <hi>Octavius</hi> moſt heartily, and my own happineſs alſo, upon this occaſion: Neither do I expect your Sentence; We are both Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors; nor am I unjuſt in challenging the Victory; for if <hi>Octavius</hi> has had the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of me, I at the ſame time do tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over my own Errors. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as to what concerns the main Queſtion, I both own a <hi>Providence,</hi> and believe in <hi>GOD;</hi> and for the reſt, I agree with you touching the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and truth of <hi>your,</hi> or (to ſpeak more properly) <hi>Our RELIGION.</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs there remain ſome few things (not in oppoſition to Truth, but need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for my fuller information) of which I deſire we may entertain ſome further Diſcourſe. But we will put off this till to morrow (the Sun being now near ſetting) that at our leiſure, and with more convenience we may throughly diſcuſs this whole <hi>Matter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEN <hi>Caecilius</hi> had thus freely utter'd his Mind, As for me (ſaid I) I
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:40984:75"/>am overjoy'd upon the account of us all, and in particular, that <hi>Octavius</hi> has done me ſo great a pleaſure by his Victory, as to deliver me from the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy of judging between my Friends. Nevertheleſs I ſhall not launch forth into the Praiſes of <hi>Octavius,</hi> becauſe I am ſenſible that I can never give him the Commendations he deſerves. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the Teſtimony of a man, and of one only, is too little: The Great <hi>GOD</hi> is his Reward, who has in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd him with ſo perſwaſive a Speech, and enabled him to overcome.</p>
            <p>THUS we all departed joyfully, <hi>Caecilius,</hi> becauſe he had believ'd; <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius,</hi> becauſe he had overcome; and <hi>my ſelf,</hi> both for the <hi>Faith</hi> of the <hi>One,</hi> and <hi>Victory</hi> of the <hi>Other.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="advert_for_French_lessons">
            <pb facs="tcp:40984:75"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Tranſlator</hi> of this <hi>Book,</hi> teaches the <hi>French</hi> Tongue according to an exact and eaſie Method. He is to be heard of at M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> 
               <hi>Gates</hi>'s Houſe in <hi>Bow-Lane,</hi> over againſt <hi>Baſing-Lane</hi>-end, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
